[Music]
so last week I told you I offered you an
interpretation of two foundational
stories right or more than two but
roughly speaking to the creation stories
because there's two of them in Genesis
and then also the story of the Buddha
and I was presenting you with a
proposition and it's a multi-layered
proposition the first proposition is
that the archetypal story structure that
we've already been discussing is
reflected in detail in those stories and
the archetypal story structure is
something like the existence of a
pre-existing state where things are
roughly functional so that you might
think of that as the state of things
going well and that's the state where
your perceptions and your plans are
sufficiently developed so that when you
act them out in the world not only do
you get what you desire but the story
itself validates itself through your
actions right because what happens when
you act something out and you get what
you intend just like when you use a map
and get where you're going not only does
that get you to where you're going but
it also validates the plan or the map
and so that's that's that's a definition
of truth that's a pragmatic definition
of truth this is the sort of thing that
I was trying to have a discussion with
about Sam Harris because the idea is
that we have to orient ourselves in a
world where our knowledge is always
insufficient we never know everything
about anything and so the question then
is how can you ever make a judgment
about whether or not you're correct and
the answer to that is something like
well you lay out a plan and you can
think about it this way if this is
actually an answer to the postmodernist
problem of how is it that you determine
whether or not your interpretation of
the world is we won't say correct
because that's not exactly right but you
know the postmodernist subjects say with
regards to the interpretation of the
text that there's a very large number of
variations of ways in which that text
can be interpreted and that's actually
true and it's the same it's a it's
actually reflection of a deeper claim
which they always off
and sometimes also make which is well if
that's true for a text which isn't as
complex as everything although it's
complex then it's even more true for
everything which is to say the world
lays itself out in a very complex manner
and you can interpret that in a very
large number of ways so who's to say
which interpretation is correct okay
fair enough it's a reasonable objection
and it's it's tied in with even a deeper
problem which is the problem of
perception itself because if the world
is laid out in a manner that's
exceptionally complex then how is it
that you can even perceive it well
that's that's partly the question that
we're trying to answer and the answer to
that is well you have evolved perceptual
structures and they're actually oriented
towards specific goals and your embodied
so the your embodiment as a
goal-directed entity is part of the
solution to the problem of perception
but it's more complicated than that so
we could say well you come equipped and
this was Kant's objection to Pure Reason
essentially that the problem is if the
facts don't speak for themselves
there's too many facts for them to speak
for themselves so you have to overlay on
top of them an interpretive framework
well where does the interpretive
framework come from well the right
answer to that is something like it
evolves right it's taken three and a
half billion years for your perceptual
structure your embodied perceptual
structure to evolve and it's done that
roughly in a trial and error process I
don't think that exhausts what's
happened over the course of evolution
but it's a good enough shorthand for the
time being so so there's the constraints
imposed on your perceptual structures by
the necessity of survival in
reproduction but there's other
constraints imposed to that you might
regard two subsets of that one is that
because you exist in a cooperative and
competitive landscape the perceptual
structures and plans that you layout
will say the maps that you layout have
to be negotiated with other people and
so that puts stringent constraints on
the number of interpretations that
you're allowed to to apply so you can
think about this in a piagetian sense
that is if there are children in a
playground and they're trying to
organize themselves to play they have to
agree on a game and the game is of
course a
sexual structure and a goal-directed
structure and a structure that the
delimits action and interactions and so
they at least have to settle on a game
and so that constrains the set of
possible actions and perceptions in the
environment to those that are deemed
socially acceptable and then you say
well what are there further constraints
and the constraints might be well let's
play the game and see if it's any fun
and that means that you have to take the
plan that you've organized consensually
and then lay it out in the actual world
and see if when you lay it out in the
world it does what it's supposed to do
in some sense what you're doing is
testing a tool so the idea that the the
range of interpretations is infinite and
unconstrained turns out to be incorrect
and now it's that that is that doesn't
mean it's easy to figure out how they're
constrained but the technical suggestion
that well there's an infinite number of
equally valid interpretations is just
not correct it's not correct and it's
not correct on biological evolutionary
ground and it's not it's also not
correct on socio-cultural grounds
because it has to be negotiated and then
you know Piaget put a further constraint
on that essentially by saying well not
only does it have to be a game and a
game that attains its end but it has to
be a game that people want to play so it
also has to satisfy some element of
subjective desire as well so that's
three levels of constraint right it has
to be a game you want to play it has to
be a game that you can play with other
people and it has to be a game that if
you play with other people actually
works in the world okay well so much for
an infinite array of options it's a very
constrained array of auctions now and I
think and that the idea that I've been
proposing to you is that what evolved
mythology does these representations
that we've been dealing with these
archetypal representations is sketch out
that landscape what what is the
landscape of playable games that's a
good way of thinking about it and so
it's it sets out a landscape it's it
sets out a description of the landscape
in which the game is going to be played
as well as the description of the lens
of the game itself and so the landscape
is roughly the core the core archetype
seems to be something like
it's it's something like the interplay
between chaos and order and chaos is
represented by hidden the serpent Isle
predator because we use our predator
detection circuits to conceptualize the
unknown because what else would we do it
that seems given that we're prey animals
and given our evolutionary history it's
very difficult to understand what else
we would possibly do because the
critical issue about venturing into the
unknown is that you might die or perhaps
a slight variant of that is something
might kill you but whatever those are
close enough to the same thing so chaos
is what causes your deterioration and
death and there's lots of ways to
conceptualize that but but reptilian
predator fire-breathing reptilian
predator isn't a bad way to start and so
the question is well what do you do in
the face of that and one answer is you
build circumscribed enclosures that's
order and then also you act as the
builder of circumscribed enclosures so
that's partly the hero now the hero is
also though that's not good enough
because the circumscribed enclosure
isn't impermeable it can be invaded it
will inevitably be invaded either from
the outside or from within right and so
we've been conceptualizing the the
predator the malevolent predator at
multiple levels of analysis throughout
our evolutionary history say but also in
our symbolic history trying to
understand the nature of that which
invades the enclosure right and we can
say well it's partly external threat
it's partly social threat but it's also
partly the threat that each individual
brings to bear on the social structure
because of our let's say our intrinsic
malevolence and so that would be the
snakes within and so that accounts for
the analogy that the Christian analogy
between the serpent in the Garden of
Eden and Satan which is a very very
strange analogy it's not obvious at all
why those two things would stack on top
of one another especially given that
when the creation story originally
emerged in the in the form I talked to
you about last week the story of Adam
and Eve the idea that the serpent in the
garden was also something that was
associated with the adversary wasn't an
implicit part of the story
that got laid on afterwards like well
what's the worst possible snake well
that's a reasonable question and then a
better question is what do you do about
the worst possible snake and one answer
is you face it
but there's other answers too like you
make sacrifices right and that's how you
stave off the dragon of temporal chaos
roughly speaking is that you learn to
conceptualize the future you see the
future as a realm of potential threat
and then you learn to give things up in
the present and somehow that satisfies
the future now so maybe you're offering
sacrifices to God and you think well why
is that well think you're going to think
about that psychologically why does that
work well you can think about the Spirit
of God the Father as an imagistic
representation of the collective spirit
of the group we'll call it the
patriarchy if you want doesn't matter
it's the thing that's common across the
group as a spirit as a psychological
force across time why do you make
sacrifices to that that is what you do
all the time you're right now you're
sacrificing your time to the spirit of
the great Father because your assumption
is is that if you do what's diligent so
you're not chasing impulsive pleasure at
the moment unless you're pathologically
interested in this class or something
like that you're not chasing impulsive
interest you're sacrificing your
impulsive interests to satisfy the
spirit of social requirement and so
you're offering a sacrifice to that
spirit in the hope that you can make a
bargain with it so that it will reward
you in the future and that reward will
be part of it partly the staving off of
insecurities which is ever no more than
to say that part of the reason that
you're getting your degree is because
you believe that you laid you in finding
employment and status and all the other
things that will stave off the dragon of
chaos so now those things were as we've
been at pains to to to point out as
those things were acted out and then
represented an image and story long
before they could be fully articulated
because we're building our knowledge of
ourselves and also our social structures
and also the world from the bottom up as
well as from the top down there's an
interplay between the two levels of
analysis okay and so so that's partly
that's part of the archetypal
underpinning and then with regards to
the stories themselves you're you're in
a map so to speak you're using a map and
with any luck its detailed enough so
that you can use it to get to the place
that you want to go and sometimes you
don't and that means that you have to
recalibrate your your journey along the
map which by the way is exactly what GPS
systems do when you go off the pathway
right they stop
that's an anxiety response from the GPS
system they stop they recalibrate and
they readjust the map now and then if
you're unfortunate this very rarely
happens anymore you'll be on a road that
isn't mapped and then the GPS system
doesn't know what to do well that
happens in real life too I mean those
are I'm using GPS for a very specific
reason those are intelligent systems as
far as I'm concerned those are the
closest things we ever designed to
intelligent systems because they can
actually orient right they orient in
real time and they're unbelievably
sophisticated systems right because they
rely on a huge satellite network and so
on and they're cybernetic systems
technically speaking they respond very
much like the way that we respond so so
anyways you know you're in un habit a
map you try to adjust the resolution of
the map so that it's mono more complex
than it needs to be to get you from
point A to point B that's it you want
minimal resolution because that enables
efficient cognitive processing it
doesn't overload you too much like when
I'm looking at this room if I look say I
want to walk down this pathway basically
what my mind does my perceptual field
and you can detect this if I look
straight ahead I can barely see you
people on the periphery you're more like
you're kind of like blurs you - I can
tell that you have heads but that's
about it when you move I can see your
hand
I can probably see your eyes but barely
so you're all very low resolution and
even though I can't detect it at the
very periphery of my vision you guys are
black and white so my color vision
disappears at the periphery even though
I can't I can't actually perceive that
so what happens is if I want to walk
down here this pathway becomes
high-resolution it becomes marked with
positive emotion all of this turns into
low resolution back here it's not even
represented and then I find out well am
i doing
properly and the answer is while I walk
forward and if I get to the goal then
I've done it properly enough and if you
know what have you stand up and get in
my way then I'm going to focus on you
and assume instantly that I haven't
mapped you properly right I put you in
the category of irrelevant entity when
in fact you have to be in the category
of strange object the thing that objects
and so well so then we inhabit those
structures all the time we're in a
structure like that a perceptual
structure and if it's working then it's
got the archetypal quality of paradise
so to speak because it's axioms are
correct and it's functional and then now
and then something comes along and
that's what the snake is the eternal
snake in the garden that pops up inside
a structure and it turns out that the
things that you weren't attending to are
the most important things rather than
the least important things and that what
does I do it blows the map into pieces
and that can happen at different levels
of severity but at the ultimate level of
severity its apocalyptic right
everything goes and that's it that's a
traumatic intrusion and essentially the
story of the Garden of Eden is the story
of a traumatic intrusion that's exactly
what it is and so what happens is that
Adam and Eve are living in unconscious
bliss roughly speaking
everything's fine they're in their
walled garden they're in a paradisal
state they're not aware of their own
vulnerability or nakedness so they're
not suffering from negative emotion
something pops up that radically expands
their vision and all of a sudden now
they can apprehend all sorts of things
that exist as threats so that's their
own nakedness and vulnerability and
temporality itself because they become
aware of the future and bang that state
of being in that paradise is forever
gone that's the strange thing about
human beings this is what what happened
to us I think is that our perceptions
developed to such a degree that we could
no longer ignore what was irrelevant we
couldn't do it because we discovered
roughly speaking once we discovered our
finite limitations in time and space we
discovered that we were surrounded by
infinite threat always and maybe that's
why people are so hyper awake because
threat wakes you up well we're in a
constant state of existential threat now
the advantage to that is that we take we
take arms up against a sea of troubles
constantly that's the advantage right
and we build enclosures and we take
precautions for the future and we live a
very long time and we generally live
quite safe lives compared to the lives
we could live and so we've traded pain
for anxiety that's another way of
thinking about it now it's still a
pretty rough trade right because who
wants to be nervous all the time but
you're alive and awake when you're
nervous and it is a form of
consciousness elevating activation
that's another way of thinking about it
so the story of Adam and Eve is the
story of the eternal fall that that's
what it is
it says look you exist in these walled
enclosures but there's something that
lurks that will always knock you off
your feet and then the question is what
is that and and the answer to that is
being formulated over very long periods
of time partly it's the probability of
predation itself that's the snake the
thing that can come in subtly and
undermine you okay but then that's
that's it what would you call it expand
it upward to include the abstract snake
which is that thing that can undermine
your conceptual schemes right so you
have your actual territory and then you
have your abstract to our territory and
in your actual territory there are
actual snakes and in your abstract
territory there are abstract snakes
right and then the worst snake of all is
malevolence and that's I think that's
technically correct because one of the
things that you view for example when
you're looking at post-traumatic stress
disorder is that it's almost always the
case that someone who suffers from
post-traumatic stress disorder which you
might think of as a real real life
reincarnation of the fall is that people
encounter something malevolent
and it breaks them because it's the
worst thing to understand
it's like suffering is one thing man
that's that's bad now vulnerability and
suffering that's bad enough but to
encounter some
who wishes that upon you and will work
to bring it about that's a whole
different category of horrible
especially what it also reflects
something back to you about yourself
because if someone else can do that to
you and they're human that means that
you partake of the same essence
strangely enough that's actually the
cure to some degree to post-traumatic
stress disorder is like if you've been
victimized you're naive and you've been
victimized the way out of that is to no
longer be naive and to no longer be
victimized and that means that you you
see this reflected in the Harry Potter
idea for example that the reason that
Harry Potter can withstand Voldemort is
because you've got a piece of a party's
being touched by it and the way that you
the way that you keep the psychopaths at
bay is to develop the inner psychopath
so that you know when when you see what
right and then but that's a voluntary
thing it's it's so it's like a it's like
a a set of tools that you have at your
disposal which is full knowledge of evil
and that does Nietzsche said if you look
into an abyss for too long you risk
having the abyss gaze back into you
right the idea is that if you look at
something monstrous you have a tendency
to turn into a monster and people are
often very afraid of looking at monsters
things exactly for that reason and then
the question is well should you turn
into a monster and the answer to that is
yes you should but you should do it
voluntarily and not accidentally and you
should do it with the good in mind
rather than falling prey to it by
possession essentially because that's
the alternative how does it possess you
that's easy
you're suffering makes you better you're
better this makes you resentful you're
resentful means meat makes you vengeful
and once you're on that road you go down
that a little bit farther man well you
end up it fantasizing in your basement
about shooting up the local high school
and then killing yourself right because
that's sort of the ultimate end of that
line of pathological reasoning being
should be eradicated because of its
intrinsic evil and I'm exactly the
person to do it and I'll cap it off with
an indication of my own lack of worth
just to hammer the point home right and
if I can garner a little post post
posthumous fame along the way well
that'll satisfy my primordial primate
dominant tired
the imaginings - at least in fantasy so
you know it's the full package if you
want to go down that route and of course
people don't like to think about that
sort of thing and it's no bloody wonder
but without the capability for mayhem
Europe you're you're you're a potential
victim - may have so you need your sword
it should be sheath but you need to have
it and it's very frequently the case if
you treat someone with post-traumatic
stress disorder there's two things you
have to do you have to help them develop
a very articulated philosophy of evil
because otherwise their brain bothers
them over and over and over what why
were you so dealing with naive how did
you become victimized why were you such
a sucker these are good questions you
don't want to have that happen to you
again you don't want to be exploited
twice okay so your eyes have to open up
we know the price of that from the
Egyptian myth right you come into
contact with Seth what happens even if
you're a god you lose an eye it's no
joke man
it's no joke and then the cure for that
is the movement down into the underworld
and with the revitalization of the
Father
that's the identification with the force
that created culture right and that then
there's you and that together then you
can withstand malevolence maybe you can
withstand tragedy and malevolence and
then that's the whole secret right
because that's what you want in life you
need to be able to whisk down tragedy
and you need to be able to withstand
malevolence because those are the forces
they're always working against you and
so it's just this is associated with the
Union idea of incorporation of the
shadow right you have to be we know this
God we know how predators work with
regards to children even if you're a
pedophilic predator and you're looking
at a landscape of children the child
that you're going to go after is the one
that's timid and won't fight back
you pick your victim and predatory
people in general or exactly like that
man they're because they're predators
they're not going to attack someone
who's who's going to fight back in fact
the issue is likely not to even come up
they're going to be looking for someone
one way or another that cannot
conceptualize what they are and then
perfect it's it's open season and it's
open season and so if you're treating
someone with post-traumatic
trustus order first they need an
introduction to the philosophy of
malevolent and second they have to learn
to become dangerous because that's the
only way out what's the alternative to
get these recurrent thoughts about their
vulnerability in the face of malevolence
and their own naivety because by
definition if someone psychopathic has
exploited you you're too naive
it's a definitional issue you can say
well that's no fault of mine how the
hell could I be prepared fair enough man
perfectly reasonable objection doesn't
solve your problem because it's an it's
an eternal problem right the internal
problem is how do you deal with tragedy
and malevolence and you can say well I'm
not prepared it's like yeah fair enough
unsurprising especially if you were over
protected as a child it's not a good
idea to over protect your kids because
the snakes are going to come into the
garden no matter what you do and so then
you instead of trying to keep the damn
snakes away what you do is you arm your
child with something that can help them
chop them into pieces and make the world
out of them so that the trick for human
thriving in the face of suffering and
malevolence is strength not protection
it's a completely different idea we also
know this clinically we know for example
that if you treat people with exposure
therapy for Agra phobia which is roughly
speaking the fear of chaos I would say
the fear of everything you don't make
them less afraid
you make the braver it's not the same
thing because with an agri-food they see
what happens to them is is the fault
they never conceptualize death and
suffering they're naive right it never
enters their theater of their
imaginations because they're protected
from it but then something happens this
often happens to women in their 40s
because they're the people most likely
to develop Agra phobia something happens
there they've been protected from chaos
by Authority their entire life so maybe
they had an overprotective father and
then they went to an overprotective
boyfriend and then they went to an
overprotective husband and maybe they
were willing to be subjugated to all
three of those because of the project
protection right so so that's the
bargain they stay weak and dependent and
maybe they have to because that's the
only way they can appeal to the person
who's hyper protective but the
they pay for that is that they're not
sufficiently competent and then
something happens in their life often in
their 40s they develop heart
palpitations maybe as a consequence of
menopause their heart starts to beat
erratically and they think oh no death
it's like well who are you going to talk
to about that
right there's no protection from
authority for that or maybe their friend
gets divorced or maybe their sister dies
or something like that it brings up the
specter of mortality and maybe the
specter of malevolence and mortality and
it brings it up in a way that authority
recourse to Authority cannot solve and
so then they have panic attacks what
happens they go out they get afraid they
feel their heart beating then they get
afraid of their heart beating because
they think oh no I'm going to die
and they think oh no I'm going to die
and I'm going to make a fool of myself
while I'm doing it and attract a lot of
attention so the two big fears come up
mortality and social judgment then they
have a panic attack it's like fighter
flights going out of control very very
unpleasant then they start to avoid the
places they've had a panic attack then
they end up not being able to go
anywhere so then
Kyah math has come back right a huge
monster a little victim and so what do
you do with them well there's no saying
note there's no time app that's done
right there naivety is over they've had
a direct contact with the threat of
mortality and social judgment they've
met the terrible mother and they met the
terrible father and there's no going
back there's no saying oh the world is
safe it's not safe not at all it's not
safe
the fact that you think it's safe means
that you were living in an unconscious
bubble that was sort of provided to you
by your culture it's a gift and now
that's been shattered and so now what do
you do well the answer is you retreat
until you're in your house and there's
nowhere you can go you're the ultimate
frozen rabbit right and your life is
hell because you can't function
the alternative is let's take apart the
things you're afraid of let's expose you
to them you know carefully and
programmatically and then you'll learn
that you can you're actually tougher
than you think you never knew that and
maybe you didn't want to take on the
responsibility because you know people
play
role in their own demise so to speak
when you had opportunity to go out and
explore or withdraw because you were
afraid you chose to withdraw because you
were afraid so it's not only that you
were over protected often it's that you
were willing to take advantage of the
fact that you were over protected and
run back there whenever you had the
opportunity you know so maybe you're a
kid in the playground right and you're
having some trouble with other kids and
you know in the back of your mind I
should deal this with deal with this
myself but you go and tell your mom and
get her to intervene and you know that
that's not right you know that you're
breaking the social contract but it's
easier and so that's what you do you run
off to an authority figure and hide
behind the Great Father right roughly
speaking well the problem with that is
you don't learn how to do it yourself so
then you have to relearn it painfully
when you're 40 so then you take people
out you say well what are you afraid of
ranked it from 1 to 10 so 10 is make a
list of 10 things you're afraid of the
least the thing you're least afraid of
will call number 10 so we'll start with
that
okay well I'm afraid of elevators okay
well let's let's look at a picture of an
elevator let's have you imagine being in
an elevator let's go out to an elevator
and let you watch the terrible jaws of
death open because that's how you're
responding to it symbolically right and
you're going to do that at it at the the
closest proximity you can manage you
find out you go do that
it works you're nervous as hell
especially a permit an anticipatory
perspective shaking you go out you stop
you watch it happen and you actually
calm down you do that 10 times it no
longer bothers you well what you've
learned that you didn't die but more
importantly than that you've learned
that you could withstand the threat of
death that's what you've learned and
then you move a little closer and then
you move a little closer and then you
move a little closer and finally you're
back in what's no longer the elevator
from a symbolic perspective it's a tomb
right it's it's it's a place of
enclosure and isolation and you learn
hmm turns out I can withstand that and
then you're met much more together much
more confident and that's often one of
the things that often happens in
situations like that I've seen this
multiple times is that
if you run someone through an exposure
training process like that and toughen
them up they'll often start standing up
to people around them in a way they
never did before because they wouldn't
stand up for themselves before because
they weren't willing to undermine the
protection see if you're protecting me
I can't bother you because I can't
afford to forsake your protection
so if I'm going to play that game I'm
going to be high hide behind you then I
can't challenge you so that's no good
because that's sometimes why people you
see this with guys very frequently
they're still deathly afraid of their
father's judgment when they're in their
30s or 40s it's like well why not
because they still want to believe that
there's someone out there that knows and
so they're willing to accept the
subjugation because it doesn't force
them to challenge the idea that there's
someone out there that knows because
that's the advantage of having your
father as a judge right because he knows
well what if he doesn't what if no one
knows any better than you well that's a
rough thing you don't until you realize
that you're not an adult right that's
really technically the point of
realization of adulthood is that no one
actually knows what you should do more
than you do I mean it's a horrible
realization because what the hell do you
know it's a terrible realization and
people will often pick slavery permanent
slavery to the spirit of the Great
Father let's say over that realization
and it's completely understandable but
the problem with it is is that there's
more to you than you think and so if you
continue to hide behind that figure then
you never have a chance to understand
that there's more to you than you think
far more to you than you think maybe
there's enough to you so that you can
actually withstand the threat of
mortality without collapsing maybe even
withstand the threat of malevolence
without collapsing who knows it's
certainly possible and it's not an
abstract question it's exactly the sort
of question that you address in the
psychotherapeutic process it's it's
always the question that you address and
the answer is often in the affirmative
because people can get unbelievably
tough and you know that because people
work in emergency wards and hospitals
right or they work in in palliative care
Awards or they work as March
very assistants I mean these people have
bloody rough jobs you know or they're on
the front line of police investigation
into you know highness
child abuse crimes and so they're
confronting malevolence on a regular
basis and you know those are very
stressful jobs but people do them and
some people do them without even being
damaged by them although that's a harder
thing because you can see horrible
things you know things you'll never
forget so so I would say the the story
in the story of Adam and Eve is a meta
story and it's a meta story for two
reasons
one is it's about how stories transform
because Adam and Eve are in this
unconscious paradise and then it
collapses and that happens to every
potential story right that's Nietzsche's
realization he said look imagine that
you live within a belief system and then
something arises to challenge the belief
system not only does the belief system
collapse but something worse happens
your belief in belief systems collapses
and that's the road tonight now it
doesn't have to because you can jump
from one belief system to another but
sometimes that doesn't work is that you
do a meta critique and you say oh I was
living in this protective structure and
it turned out to be flawed okay one
alternative is jumped to another
protective structure fine another
alternative is protective structures
themselves are not to be trusted
bang you're in chaos how the hell are
you going to get out of that that's the
pathway to nihilism well you can you can
you can work your way through that
that's difficult or you can do what Jung
would regard as a soul damaging move and
you can sacrifice your new knowledge
Andrey identify with something rigid and
restricted which is what I would say is
happening to some degree with the people
in your Europe who are turning to a
regressive nationalism as an alternative
to to the current state of chaos it's
like I know that people need to identify
with local groups I understand that but
that they risk the danger of making the
state the ultimate God and that's order
but that's not a good replacement for
chaos it's just another kind of
catastrophe right
too much order too much chaos both
catastrophes you want to stand in the
middle somehow and mediate between the
two and
that's where you have your real
strengths because then it isn't that
you've discovered a safe place to be
even the bloody right-wingers are after
a safe place right they just want it to
be the state yeah exactly well there's
no safe places and the next issue is do
you really want a safe place is that
what you want you want to be so weak
that you want to be protected from
threat
what the hell kind of life is that
you're a paralyzed rabbit in a hole
that's no life for a human being you
should be confronting danger and the
unknown and malevolence because and the
reason for that too is this is the weird
paradox this is and I believe this is
the paradox first of all that was
discovered in part by Buddha but also
laid forth very clearly in Christianity
which is that the solution to the
problem of tragedy in malevolence is the
willingness to face them now who the
hell would ever guess that it's
completely paradoxical it's a completely
paradoxical suggestion is that well why
does it work well because the more you
confront the two of them the more you
grow and maybe you can grow so that
you're actually larger than the chaos
and malevolence itself and you think
well what's the evidence for that and
that's easy that's what people do that
is how we learn like every time you
expose your child to something new a
playground
what are they exposed to chaos and
malevolence now there's more to it than
that obviously because kids play and
they you know they promote each other
and they form friendships and all of
that but in the playground itself there
is the complexity of the social
structure and the malevolence of the
bully it's right there and that you
throw your kid in there and you say
adapt and they do okay so they can do it
at a small scale it's not trivial the
playground is a complicated place the
kid can adapt well how much can you
scale that up can you scale that up to
from the chaos and order and malevolence
of the playground to chaos and order and
malevolence itself well that's the
question
well I don't think there's any reason to
answer that in the negative so because
we don't know the full extent of the
human being and it is the problem that's
worked out so in the Buddhist story for
example what
happens after so buddha's world
collapses in the same way that Adam and
Eve's world collapses it's a consequence
of repetitive exposure to mortality and
death what happens to Buddhas he
realizes that the little protected city
that his father made for him the walled
garden it's exactly the same motif
that's in this Adam and Eve story is is
it's it's what it's fatally flawed that
kind of protection cannot exist and he
discovers that in pieces right which is
exactly what happens to children is that
they go out they discover a limit they
run back and the parents can help them
with the limit they run out they
discover limit they run back but some at
some point they run out they discover a
limit they run back and the parents have
nothing to say to them because they've
hit the same limit that the parents hit
which is like well what are you going to
do with your life how are you going to
how are you going to operate in this
archetypal universe while your parents
can only say well they can say you
identify with the proper archetypal
figures they do that they at least act
that out for you but at some point it's
a problem that they cannot solve for you
without making you weaker that's the
thing you know so it's an interesting
thing that I've learned in therapy
because one of the things you have to
learn as a therapist is how do you not
take your clients problems home with you
it's a very common existential problem
that beginning therapists face because
they're afraid it's like while you're
dealing with people all the time you
have serious problems sometimes it's
mental illness although less frequently
than you'd think and sometimes it's just
that they're having a good catastrophe
right there their parents have cancer or
something like that or the father has
Alzheimer's and they're unemployed they
have a drug problem or they have a
schizophrenic son or like these aren't
mental illness problems right those are
just catastrophes and so people are
discussing those with you all the time
how do you avoid being crushed by that
or avoid taking at home and the answer
to that is you don't steal the problem
that that's the answer it's like you
have some problems if you come and talk
to me I'll help you figure out how to
solve them I will not tell you how to
solve I won't steal your problems
because what we're trying to do in
therapy is number one solve your problem
number
to turn you into a great solver of
problems and the second one is way more
important than the first one and so you
never solve someone's problem by
removing from them the opportunity to
solve their problem that's theft
that's the eatable situation that's the
eatable situation that's the
overprotective mother now farther can
play that rule too we're talking about
archetypal representations like I'll
protect you at the cost of your ability
to protect yourself no wrong that's
that's a sin that's a good way of
thinking about that is not what you do
with people not with your children not
with your partner not with yourself you
don't do that that destroys people's
adaptive competence and it disarms them
in the face of chaos and malevolence and
that's a terrible unisen someone oh darn
armed in the world like that it's a
terrible thing to do so and if people
aren't strong enough to manage it then
they get resentful and then you know
when you get the downhill spiral that
goes along with that okay so the meta
story is partly you're in a mat you're
you have a map but it's insufficient and
things will come up to disrupt it and
sometimes the disruption is catastrophic
everything falls apart that's what
happens to the Buddha and that's what
happens to Adam and Eve and the rest of
the biblical stories are actually an
attempt to put that back together now
that's being assembled as I said it's
been assembled over centuries right okay
we've got the problem the problem is the
apocalypse the ever-present reality of
the apocalyptic fall that's the problem
and so you could say well what is that
it's the insufficiency of all potential
conceptual schemes right your conceptual
schemes are insufficient to deal with
the complexity of the world it's a
permanent problem so what do you do you
stop relying on your conceptual schemes
that's part of the answer you start
relying on your instead on your ability
to actively generate conceptual schemes
in the face of chaos and malevolence and
so that makes you someone that
identifies with your creative capacity
your creative courageous capacity for
articulation and action in the face of
the unknown rather than some formulaic
approach to the
territory and that it not and that the
idea is that that elevates your
character to the point where you can
withstand tragedy and malevolence
without becoming corrupt and that
provides a permanent solution to the
problem well then you might say
cynically what's your evidence that
that's a permanent solution an answer
that is while the evidence isn't all in
yet first of all because people only
live that way partially and so we
haven't put the hypothesis to the full
test and second we don't know what our
limitations are we have no idea what our
limitations are and they're they're both
greater and lesser than we imagined
because you you know you have to ask
yourself like if people stopped adding
voluntarily to the misery of the world
and devoted themselves to setting things
straight setting themselves straight and
setting the things around them straight
what would happen and the answer to that
is well there'd be a hell of a lot less
unnecessary misery in the world so that
might not be a bad place to start but
apart from that there's very little that
we can say could we overcome the
catastrophe of mortality why not
you think that's beyond our capacity
could we make the world a place where no
one was suffering any more than
necessary and still allow the world to
exist well possibly because we don't
know the limitations of our capacity
we're only running at 40 percent if that
I would say we don't make full use of
all the people that are in the world we
don't have our situation set up so that
the gifts that they could offer to
everyone are fully realized we haven't
set the systems up for that yet so we
waste people like mad and then we waste
ourselves like mad and so I would say
this is something also that's it one of
the things that's really interesting
about the Old Testament Jews this is I
think one of the reasons that their book
has become so central is because what
happens in the Old Testament after the
fall is that Israel produces a series of
states right rise of state and then a
fall and then a rise of another state
and then a fall so it's the same thing
except it's happening at a political
level the political state rises it gets
corrupt it falls it rises out of the
ashes again gets corrupt and Falls I
think that happen
times in the Old Testament and one of
the things that's very interesting is
the reaction of the Jews they always say
it was our fault instead of taking the
Cain and Abel roots oh and I'm going to
tell you the Cain and Abel story right
away instead of taking the Cain and Abel
route they always say if the state
collapsed it was because we did
something wrong that's very different
than saying you know it's arbitrary fate
it's the nature of arbitrary fate or the
structure of reality that we're doomed
to collapse into chaos and that's an
indication of the corruption of being
well you can take that route if you want
it's the corruption of being well good
luck with that so what are you going to
do about that that's easy
start you'll start to work for the
destruction of being that's what you
will do the alternative is to say this
terrible thing happened and somehow it's
my fault well at least that ly opens you
up the pathway to doing something about
it and maybe it's actually the case
maybe terrible things happen because
you're just not who you should be at
least it's a night you know that's true
to some degree right you know it because
things happen to you all the time and
you think well you know if I just would
have played that game straight if I
would have put this thing in order that
wouldn't have happened it's like okay
fine what's the ultimate extent of that
das esq said at one point that every
human being was not only responsible for
everything that happened to him or her
but also simultaneously responsible for
everything that happened to everyone
else it's a very it's a I would say it's
almost a hallucinogenic idea right it's
a it's a transcendent idea and it can go
very wrong sometimes depressed people
for example get hyper responsible for
what's happened and just crushes them
and so it's a it's a mode of thinking
that can produce its attendant
pathologies but there's something about
it that's there's something about it
that's metaphysically true so all right
so I'm going to tell you the story of
Cain and Abel now I really like this
story it's it's very short it's only
about a paragraph long which is very
interesting because it it's one of these
examples where there's a it's like a
genie that the story there's so much
condensed into it that it's almost
unbelievable and
there's even ambiguity condensed into it
which is which is very very interesting
because it actually makes the story more
complex and sophisticated so let me tell
you the story now the first thing I want
to tell you some things about the story
first so we've got the original
paradisal state and then the collapse
and so now metaphysically speaking we're
in the collapse we're in the we're in
the post fall condition we're still
occupying a mythological landscape right
this isn't history as we normally
understand it it's meta history so when
we talk about Cain and Abel Cain and
Abel we're actually talking about the
first two real human beings because Adam
and Eve a were created by God and being
were in Paradise and so that's not the
normative condition of human beings
right that's a that's a special time
that's outside of normal time and space
Cain and Abel by contrast they're in
history because in some sense history
actually starts a couple of times in the
Old Testament it starts with the
creation of being it starts with the
formation of the garden it starts with
the fall it starts with Cain and Abel it
starts it over again with Noah and then
it starts with Abraham which is really
where what we would recognize more as
conventional history begins so there's a
number of starts of history but this is
one of them Cain and Abel are the first
two human beings who are they they're
the adversarial brothers hero and
adversary there are types of Christ and
Satan the well-known supposition you see
that hostile brother motif well it's an
archetypal motif and the hostile
brothers are the part of you that's
striving for the light that's one-half
and the part of you that's embracing the
darkness and so that's part of you it's
part of the social structure that's Seth
and Osiris it's part of the natural
order in some sense that's the
benevolent and destructive elements of
nature right you see that negativity
running through all the archetypal
representations but Cain and Abel are
the hostile brothers and the KE Cain is
roughly that part of you that says Oh to
hell with it and means it right and that
means you'll work for your own pain and
destruction at the same time that you're
working for the pain and destruction not
only of your brother but
but more particularly of the brother
that you admire because that's actually
a lot more entertaining right if you're
going to become destructive and you go
destroy something bad that hardly
qualifies as destruction what you want
to do is find something great and
destroy that that's destruction that's
revenge
none of this coding punishment where it
deserves to be what you want to do and
this is partly why the story of Christ
is archetypal and the archetypal story
is when you cannot push beyond what's
the worst possible punishment what's the
worst possible punishment meted out for
the least the least the most innocent
person you hit an archetypal end there
so you define most innocent person you
can do that any way you want
define most innocent person define worst
possible punishment can join the two
things you get an archetypal story and
the reason for that is you can't push
beyond it and so if you want to destroy
something you want to destroy an ideal
not something that's flawed and so Kate
and Abel are set up exactly that way so
I'll read you the story and I'll
interleave some interpretations along
with it so an atom anew Eve his wife and
she conceived and bore Cain and said I
have got the man from the Lord and she
again bare his brother Abel and Abel
with the keeper of sheep but Cain was a
tiller of the ground
okay so Abel's a shepherd and Cain is a
farmer the Shepherd is a archetypal
symbol because the Shepherd is the
leader of a flock and the Shepherd is
the heroic leader of a flock and the
reasons this is Middle Eastern mythology
let's say well if you were a shepherd
what did you do you took your slingshot
in your stick and you defended your nice
juicy plump delicious sheep against
lions right so it was no joke man you
you were a tough cookie if you were a
shepherd because while you were acting
as the guardian of that you're acting as
the Guardian against predation roughly
speaking and you weren't armed very well
I mean well you can just think about it
for a minute it's to think about
fighting off a lion with a with a
slingshot or with a bow and arrow with a
spear I mean you have to have a lot of
courage to manage that
especially successfully so Abel was a
keeper of sheep and Cain was a tiller of
the ground which isn't as heroic to roll
and so right off the bat you get this
dichotomy between the two roles it's
also a great interest that Cain is the
older brother and Abel is the younger
brother and you see that very frequently
in mythology because the older brother
is the one that's privileged by status
right so he's got he's got privilege
Cain because he's the elder brother that
also means that if there are possessions
to be handed down the generations the
older brother gets them now
interestingly enough Cain has privileged
but he's not the one that's favored by
God that's and I think that's absolutely
absolutely brilliant that it's set up
that way because it's actually Abel who
doesn't have the right that the first
Lord has who actually turns into the
person who's the proper manifestation of
the ideal it's because Cain has things
given to him you might think well that
that's great he's privileged what a
wonderful thing for Cain it's like don't
be so sure about that and partly because
one of the things that you'll find
because many of you will be well off
when you have children is one of the
problems with being reasonably wealthy
when you have children is that you
deprive them of privation because the
law of what makes people mature is
necessity and if you have for example if
you have more money than you know what
to do with roughly speaking it's very
difficult to say no to your children
when they want something because why are
you going to say no you can just provide
it well what makes you think that that's
what you should do well you can have
anything you want well what happens you
devalue what you want and your desires
continue to grow well that's not very
helpful so it's not obvious at all that
providing people with an excess let's
say a privilege is something that's good
for them from a psychological
perspective they need to hit the proper
limitations and if you're fortunate it
becomes very difficult to deprive your
children properly so you'll you'll fight
with that it's a big problem that's what
happens when you get spoiled children
roughly speaking right they get every
they get everything by doing nothing
well that's not a good lesson because
that won't work in the world it
worked very counterproductive leigh-anne
in process of time it came to pass that
Cain brought of the fruit of the ground
an offering unto the Lord and Abel he
also brought of the firstlings of his
flock and of the fat thereof and the
Lord had respect unto Abel and his
offering but unto Cain and his offering
he had no respect and Cain was very
wroth angry and his countenance fell
okay so again there's a tremendous
amount packed into that this is the
first time that we see the motif of
sacrifice right and so I mentioned to
you before how these archaic people
conceptualized the world right it's a
dome with a disc of land and underneath
that a disc of water fresh and
underneath that a disc of salt water so
that's the world and then up in the
heavens that's where God is and so God's
up in the sky and we talked about why
that might be and part of that is well
when you look at the night sky you look
at what transcends your current reality
and you look at what inspires awe so
there's a God exists where awe is
experienced fine that's a perfectly
reasonable that's a perfectly reasonable
hypothesis when you think that what
you're trying to do is formulate what
constitutes the transcendent because if
you exist within a conceptual structure
and you encounter that which is outside
the conceptual structure you will feel
off that's a combination of fear
paralysis right and the combination of
overwhelming possibility and you can
experience that for example if you
listen to a great piece of music what
happens the hair on the back of your
neck stands up why because you're a prey
animal and you just puffed up to look
bigger that's why you have that
experiences pile of erection and it's
part of awe so when you see a cat pop up
because a big dog is in front of it
that's what the cats feeling it's like
oh my god pop right so you when you
encounter that which transcends your
your limited sphere of apprehension then
you experience aw you look at the night
sky that's what happens music can do
that and all sorts of things that we do
can evoke that sense and so they located
the transcendent value in that which
inspired awe fight reasonable now you
can argue
about the utility of the personification
right because God the Father was
personified in human form but that's a
very sophisticated idea too because as
we already found in the Old Testament
there's an there's an association
between whatever God is yahwah or Elohim
and and creating order out of chaos and
something about each individual human
being and so I don't believe that the
personification of God the Father in the
Old Testament is archaic and and
primitive at all I think it's one of the
most sophisticated things that people
ever developed the idea is that the
ultimate transcendent value is the
capacity to generate order out of chaos
using linguistic ability let's say and
that each person has that as an
essential element of their being like
argue with that see how far you get that
is one hell of a vicious
conceptualization and I would also say
it's the bedrock upon which our legal
system rests so you don't move that
easily you move that and many things
fall and there are things that you may
say you don't believe but you ask them
out all the time in fact if you didn't
act them out people would set you
straight very very rapidly because
basically what other people want from
you even though they don't conceptualize
it in this terms is that you Accord them
the respect due the the incarnation of
the logos that's exactly what it means
to interact with someone properly so
it's you can say what you want about
what you believe it doesn't matter what
matters is what you act out all right so
also now we have this conceptualization
of what's transcendent that's emerged as
a part partially perhaps as emotional
contagion that which inspires awe is
that which is transcendent and it's
associated with these underlying ideas
about the creation of order out of chaos
and the instantiation of that spirit in
human beings
that's all lurking in the background and
then we have this other idea which we
already talked about which is that
there's a patriarchal or paternal spirit
that represents the community at large
stretched across time you can think
about that as the spirit of the
ancestors so it's the past it's the
present but that's also projected into
the future that's the thing you bargain
with for your life in the future I'm
going to sacrifice myself to get a
degree
why is that because the spirit of my
culture will reward me in the future
that's the sacrifice
okay well took people we were
chimpanzees for God's sake it took us a
long time to figure this out chimpanzees
don't sacrifice the present for the
future you know you got to ask yourself
how long did it take human beings to
figure out that there was a future and
then what to do about it I mean this
isn't some we didn't go from chimpanzee
to fully articulated human being in one
in one step it was created knowledge and
that was extraordinarily painful what
did we learn from observation something
like storing up goods for the future
helps us live imagine how difficult that
is you know imagine that you're you're a
farmer back wouldn't but that was an
extraordinarily you were barely scraping
out a living doing that it was hand to
mouth at best all right so now it's
winter and you've got your damn seeds in
your cellar right what are you going to
do you're starving you're going to eat
them or are you going to wait and plant
them again in the spring because that's
your damn choice and so the people who
decided to eat them well some of the
people who decided to save them died
well let's say more of the people who
decided to eat them died and so this
sort of knowledge was was gathered with
an unbelievable agony you don't get what
what you have what you want right now
for you that's nothing because you're
very much accustomed to getting what you
want all the time right now roughly
speaking you know compared to people who
live from hand to mouth but back when
things were much rougher the idea that
you had to sacrifice something of value
now to be paid off in the future man
that was a rough thing to accept okay so
what happened so people figured this out
somehow they figured out that you could
make an offering of something you valued
and that might help set the world
straight how did they conceptualize that
well they conceptualize it ritually they
were acting it out to begin with it's
like the PIA jetty an idea you know when
I would when I look at that cup part of
the looking is this right it's the
adjustment of my body to the shape of
the cup as part of my understanding well
Piaget is here one of these days great
observations
that we use our bodies to represent
things long before we understand what it
is that we're representing which is to
say no more than we act things out
we're dramatic creatures right we use
drama and the sacrificial ritual is a
drama that points to a higher
psychological truth and the higher
psychological truth is let go of what's
in let go of what you value now and
perhaps that will pay off Multi manifold
in the future you're making a bargain
and then you might say well who are you
making a bargain with and you could say
well nature but that's not exactly right
it's not exactly right because let's say
I have something of value in a social in
the social organization and I'm going to
I'm going to let it go because I'm
relying on a corresponding reward or a
greater reward in the future it's a
contractual relationship with other
people it's not a relationship with
nature it's that we've organized
ourselves into a social structure and
we're willing to maintain the integrity
of the social structure across time so
that if I give up something now I can be
paid for it in the future and the rules
that the deal is that we're going to try
to keep the future the same as the
present so that those contracts can be
can be met in the future that's money
that's what money is right here's some
money you made of sacrifice that's why
you get the money what is the money
signify it's a promise from the
community that the labor that you
invested can be stored and then brought
forward for your own purposes in the
future so it's actually part of the
social contract so the thing you're
sacrificing to is the spirit of society
that produces the social contract and so
that's conceptualized as God the Father
well how else would you conceptualize it
it's it's the spirit of the dominance
hierarchy that's the right way to think
about it so it's the it's what's common
across all the members of the dominant
hierarchy across time
well it's something you can negotiate
with true or not what the hell do you
think you're doing when you make a
contract what's the law it's all of this
it's the manifest
mission of that patriarchal spirit
across time and space and what do you do
you sacrifice to it well so back 4,000
years ago 5,000 years ago however old
this story as it's probably older than
that this is the best people could do
with regards to realization and they got
it quite right because they also noted
that God was happier if you actually
sacrificed something of value and so
there's a tremendous complexity and that
idea because one of the things I could
say and this is something you can
pointed out let's say you're miserable
and unhappy okay here's a cure find
what's valuable and let it go so we
could say well maybe it's a relationship
that you have maybe its relationship
with your parents right and the
relationship is pathological but you're
locked into it you value it and no
wonder because it's a relationship with
your parents and you're suffering
terribly because of it or what do you do
maybe you let it go it's a sacrifice and
the idea is that well that will clear
the future for you well very frequently
when people are suffering terribly not
always - sometimes you just suffer
stupidly blindly and without recourse
you know you get cancer and then you die
so we have no idea how to deal with that
but sometimes the reason that you're
suffering is because you just won't let
go of the thing that's biting you you
think well I can't let go of and I've
had clients like this I can't stop
communicating with my mother who phones
me three times a day every day of my
life and never says anything that isn't
unbelievably critical and demeaning I
can't let that go like well that's not
such a good idea
the funny thing too often when people
let something like that go it goes away
sorts itself out and then comes back so
they don't even end up losing it but
unless they're willing to let it go to
sacrifice it they make no headway
whatsoever and so one of the rules is if
people are impeding your development you
sacrifice your relationship with them
right it's a very very rough rule so
in process of time it came to pass that
Cain brought of the fruit of the ground
an offering unto the Lord and Abel he
also brought of the firstlings of his
flock and of the fat thereof now that's
interesting this is this is where a
close reading matters so we don't know
what Cain's offering is it's not much
described but we do know something about
Abel's offering and what we know is that
by the standards of the time it's a high
quality offerings so it's the firstborn
and it's the fat that high-calorie right
I mean you know we think of fat as a
dietary danger but if you're hungry
that's really wrong right because fat is
unbelievably high-calorie and so what's
happening is the story points out quite
clearly that what Abel decides to offer
to God is of high quality so it's the
real thing
it's the real thing he's paying a price
okay and so then it's burned well why is
it burned well you know this is back
again thinking from an archaic
perspective well gods in the sky you
can't throw your lamb up into the sky
it'll just fall back down and so the
people knew because they've mastered
fire that smoke and savour rose and so
you could detect the quality of an
offering as a consequence of burning and
then that would go up in the spirit of
the fire would go up to the sky and God
could detect whether or not your
offering was of a reasonable quality you
know it's concretize obviously but you
don't want to make the assumption that
the people who were our forebears were
stupid just because they thought using
metaphors that aren't the same as our
metaphors they were still mapping out
the damn territory in Owens and and
you'd look you can read a book like
you're above the authors of the book or
you can read a book as if it might have
something to teach you and I would say
well sometimes the book isn't worth
reading but if a book has been around
for a very long period of time and a
very large number of people have thought
that perhaps there's something in it
sometimes they're right so and it's a
tricky thing and it might also depend on
how you read it but I found that this
sort of investigation was a lot more
useful if I started from the
presupposition that maybe there was
something I didn't know instead of you
know so funny for example I taught a
first year course about ten years ago on
the psychology of religion it was so
interesting dealing with the
eighteen-year-old students because
they're completely dismissive of
religious ideas and I thought God you
guys you don't know anything and you
have this specific kind of blindness
that a set of very intelligent social
psychologists also identified which was
blindness blindness because it actually
turns out that the least the less you
know about a topic the more you
overestimate the quality of your
knowledge so I thought we're in this
situation where kids who don't even know
how to act in the world they don't know
anything will come to university and
start up with the proposition that there
is stood critics of judeo-christian
culture which of which they know nothing
they know nothing about it they knew
nothing about history they know nothing
about philosophy nothing about
literature but they're absolutely
certain that they're correct in their in
the criticisms that they're bringing
forth it's absolutely unbelievable
so anyways and it's not helpful because
then you don't you don't get to learn
and you aren't well see you know what
happens if you don't learn okay so
anyway so it looks like Abel's doing a
good job that's the implication the
story doesn't say Abel is doing a really
good job with his sacrifices it just
hints at it and I like that because
because it leaves that ambiguity it's
like maybe you're working really hard
and your brother's working really hard
and you really can't tell the difference
between your quality of work and his
quality of work but for some reason he's
succeeding like mad that happens right
because there's an arbitrary element to
life and so the story says well the Lord
has respect unto Abel and his offering
and there's an implication that maybe
the reason for that is that you know
Cain's offerings are a little
second-rate but the story doesn't come
over to Club you over the head with that
idea it just leaves it as a as an
ambiguous possibility and the reason for
that is sometimes you make sacrifices
and maybe they're even real ones and
they don't pay off or they pay off for
someone better and so there is this
arbitrary nature of the the transcendent
that you're attempting to deal with it
rewards and doesn't reward more or less
of its own accord or there's an element
of that and so it's ambiguous in the
text even though there's a hint that
you know perhaps Abel is doing a better
job than Cain so I like that I think
it's very sophisticated so what happens
well Cain makes his offerings and God
isn't happy with them now we don't know
how Cain figures out that God isn't
happy with his offerings we get some
hints of that too but the story does
tell us that's what happens and so then
we get the psychological response on the
part of pain now one response could be
Jesus I must be doing something wrong I
better straighten myself out you know I
better come up with a better quality
offering and try that again
that isn't what happens what happens
instead is that Cain becomes angry Roth
and his countenance falls and so what
does that mean it means this right it
means he is not happy he's angry and out
for revenge and so one of the I've been
thinking about this a lot lately with
regards to the literature on inequality
because there's a very good literature
that shows for example that there's
there's a as a measure called the Gini
coefficient and the Gini coefficient is
a numerical index of the relative
inequality of a geographical locale so
for example if you went to Newfoundland
where everyone is roughly not very rich
or North Dakota say almost everyone
there is say lower middle class
something like that or upper working
class something like that very little
variability low Gini coefficient okay if
you go to Miami Beach say where
everyone's rich low Gini coefficient
because it isn't an index of absolute
wealth or absolute poverty it's an index
of relative poverty and so if everyone's
rich the relative poverty is low and if
everyone's poor the relative poverty is
low now one question is where is the
crime and you might think while the
crime is where the absolute poverty is
high right or the absolute wealth is low
that's where the crime is that's wrong
if it's if things are relatively
distributed in an egalitarian manner the
male-on-male crime especially homicide
is low and it's also the case where
everyone is rich but if you go into
places where there's some rich people
but not very many and there's a lot of
people who are comparatively poor than
the male homicide rapes rates and
violent crime rate
up substantially it's a consequence of
male-on-male competition and so what you
could derive from that and maybe even
reasonably is that you should flatten
out today I'm income into its
distribution because you're
destabilizing the society by
facilitating male criminal aggression
you can make a good case for that you
know in places like Colombia where the
Gini coefficient got unbelievably
extreme society got so violent that it
could barely hold itself together so so
you can make a conservative argument for
redistribution of income using the
observation that if the income
distribution gets too extreme the whole
bloody thing starts to destabilize it
might fall but but then you also might
say wait a minute
is it inequality that's driving the
violence or is it resentment of the
inequality that's driving the violence
now that's a tough question because you
might say well what if the game is
rigged and there's no way of moving up
the power hierarchy
well then maybe anger and the desire for
revolution is the appropriate response
but that doesn't really mean to me that
the response should be the sort of thing
that you see in high Gini coefficient
neighborhoods which is interracial
intra-racial violence between men so for
example in neighborhoods where there's
high murder rates the the murders are
always between young men and they're
always within race and so that doesn't
seem to me to be exactly a politically
revolutionary move right it's more like
it's more like violent competition for
the sake of attaining status and you
might say well that's reasonable but
because the inequality is there and then
need to find status because it's part of
what drives them forward it's part of
what makes them attractive to women it's
a necessity
well the question is do you attain
status through destruction or do you
start making your offerings put in your
offerings in order and that's something
we really need to figure out because
that's a fundamental political question
it's a fundamental political question
anyways what happens in this story is
that khane decides that the fact that
god isn't accepting his offerings means
that he's entitled to become angry and
and and negative it's good those two
things are both put together right he's
Roth he's angry and he's also depressed
and so he's in a state of mind that well
I think the best characterization for
that is hostile resentment because it's
unfair it's like yeah it's unfair so
what are going to do about it
can you get destructive about it you're
going to change your approach well Cain
he does the ultimate thing and this is
what people do when they do the ultimate
thing because that kind of hostile
resentment has an archetypal endpoint
and the archetypal end point is the
point that you get when you're hostile
and resentful because you haven't been
successful and then you go sit in your
mother's basement for about 10 years and
then you start imagining just how nice
it would be if you shot up the local
high school so that everybody knew your
name and what happens is you go from I'm
irritated because things aren't working
out for me very well - I'm irritated I
and I hate those people for whom things
are working out well - I'm irritated and
I hate the fact that the world is set up
so that this has happened to me and then
you go - well because I'm irritated and
hate the world I'm going to do whatever
I can that will destroy it most rapidly
and with the with the highest possible
amount of pain and suffering conceivable
and at that point then you don't just go
shoot up the high school you go up and
shoot up the elementary school and so if
you're wondering what kind of pathway
people walk down to get to that point
that's the pathway and the ultimate cap
of that is well I'll kill the kids
because well we already know that
killing the innocent is a lot more
effective than killing the guilty and
then just to cap it off I'll blow my
head off at the end just to show you
just how goddamn pointless it all is and
so that's the logical extension of
Kane's attitude and you might think well
that's a bit of an over-reading and I
would say it's not an over-reading at
all it's exactly what happens in the
text so it's exactly what follows it so
fine so Cain is not happy and so who is
he not happy with well he's not happy
with God so what does that mean well
we've already unpacked this he's not
happy with the social contract because
that's part of the spirit the
patriarchal spirit let's say man there's
more to it than that
because we already we've already
analyzed what God the idea of God might
represent in the background of this
story he's not happy with the
transcendent he's not happy with the
idea of the logos all of that no faith
in the transcendent nothing but he does
nothing but despise
the social contract and he's got no
faith whatsoever in the the logos let's
say the word that brings chaos are the
border he's all got nothing but contempt
for all of that and you know certainly
you know people like that and if you
don't know them you just go on YouTube
and read the comments and you'll see all
sorts of people like that so so anyway
so God has a little child with him and
he says well what why are you angry and
and why why are you upset and Cain says
then God says if you do well won't you
be accepted and if you don't do well sin
lies at your door and unto thee shall be
his desire and thou shalt rule over him
okay
that's a very mangled translation I
would say so I'm going to take it apart
so what God says is while you're angry
and you're upset it's like well what's
your problem
and then God tells Cain if you did
things properly they would work out for
you was the last thing he wants to hear
because what Cain wants to believe is
that the reason he's not doing very well
is because there's no sense having any
faith in the logos the transcendent is
is evil and aimed exactly against him
and the entire social contract is faulty
that's what he wants to hear but that is
what God says God says wait a minute
maybe you're doing something wrong well
that's maybe a worse message then
everything else is corrupt it's like
you're having a problem because you're
just not everything you could be well
and then God says something really nasty
and you can't help from this lines I
read a bunch of translations to try to
figure out exactly what it bent so this
is what God tells Caden
he says you're in a room in a house and
there's something at the door and he
uses a metaphor God uses metaphor it's a
sexually a lot aroused predatory cat and
you invited in you've invited in you
know that it has evil intent you invited
in to mate with you right and you it's
it's union with you it's this malevolent
force this it's sexual union with you
has produced an offspring and that
offspring is what possesses you and so
not only have you done something wrong
you've you've invited the Spirit
wrongdoing into your life and you
creatively intermingled it with it
voluntarily to bring forth a monster of
your own creation so that's what God
tells Cain it's like look it's bad
enough that God says you know you should
get your act together because maybe
that's why things aren't going so well
for you
before you criticize the transcendent
and the world and the structure of being
maybe you're doing something wrong but
it's worse than that he says not only
are you doing something wrong you bloody
well know you're doing something wrong
and you and you're doing it creatively
and with intent
so not only are things not going well
for you but you've played a creative
role in producing that situation and so
God basically says I am taking zero
responsibility for rejecting your
sacrifice it's all on you and so Cain
leaves and he's like seriously not happy
with that
response because he wanted to hear pat
pat you're a victim of circumstance and
everything is conspiring against you and
really being god I should get my act
together and just give you what you want
because obviously being God I'm wrong
and you're right well that is what
happens it's exactly the opposite that
it's completely on you that's the that's
the judgment and so Cain leaves and
believe me he's he was Roth before his
countenance had fallen before but it's
nothing like it is now and so he hits
the next stage and he thinks okay I'm
going to take my revenge what am I going
to do I'm going to find the most
innocent and worthwhile thing that's
favorite of God and I'm going to kill it
and that's what he does so it doesn't
matter that his brother and Abel you
know we're drawing the inference Abel's
done the right things everyone likes him
everything's flourishing for Abel he's a
good guys one of those people that you
meet that has everything and then you
meet them and you wish you could hate
them but you can't because they're
really good people and then you really
hate them because not only do they have
everything but it appears that they
deserve it and there's nothing that sort
of sits in your soul and rots it more
than that realization and so that's the
situation with Cain and so Cain thinks
Cain talked with Abel his brother and it
came to pass when they were in the field
but Cain rose up against Abel his
brother and slew him so that's so
interesting because look look what
happens to
here so he's not doing well he's
separated from the transcendent and from
society
he's bitterly resentful and now he goes
out and kills the very thing that he
most wants to be so he destroys his own
ideal right he demolishes his own ideal
that's how far his resentment has pushed
him and so he's he's done right but he
doesn't matter because it enables him to
take revenge so he doesn't care it's
like it's like the the suicidal school
shooter that blows off his head at the
end of his mayhem it's like he doesn't
matter to him it's part of the same art
form and the Lord says unto Cain where
is Abel thy brother and Cain said I know
I don't know am I my brother's keeper
well that's a good question that's why
it's posed in the story because the
answer that it's supposed to be yes and
God says what have you done the voice of
your brother's blood cries unto me from
the ground that's actually the motif
that Dostoyevsky explores I would say in
crime and punishment because what
happens is that the Skolnick Cobb is
Cain for all intents and purposes and he
commits a murder but he gets away with
it well so he thinks so he thinks no one
suspects him he buries the money he
can't stand to touch the body he buries
it in a in a abandoned lot and he's
drawn there now and then to look at
where it is but he can't touch it
because the money it's so funny because
the money before he kills the pawnbroker
is not the same as the money after he
kills the pawnbroker and the Restonic
off before he kills the pawnbroker is
not the same as the risk Olenick off
after he kills the Paulding broker in
fact they're not the same at all and so
the Skolnick have is tormented by God
you could say but not from the external
world
he sets the crime up quite nicely it's
that this the spirit against which he
transgressed tortures him from within
and there's no escape from and so
eventually what happens in crime and
punishment is the Skolnick ov continues
to manifest himself as guilty in every
possible way until he receives the
punishment that he desires because it's
the only way that he can set things
right he actually he actually he
essentially turns himself in
eventually because he can't tolerate
what he's done so well so that's the
idea the voice of thy brother's blood
cries unto me from the ground it's guilt
and now you're cursed from the earth
which has opened her mouth to receive
thy brother's blood from thy hand when
you till the ground it will not
henceforth yield unto you it strength a
fugitive and a vagabond shalt thou be in
the earth you know and you might say
well why does God not just strike Kain
dead and the answer to that perhaps is
that wouldn't be sufficient punishment
that's what it looks like to me it's
like what's the punishment you live with
what you did right and I don't want
anybody taking out either because then
you won't have to live with what you did
so that's the punishment and Cain says
unto the Lord my punishment is greater
than I can bear
like yea behold you have driven me out
this day from the face of the earth and
from thy face shall I be hid that's the
same as what happens to Adam in the
Garden of Eden remember Adam hides from
God and he has his reasons
and now Cain is alienated from God
there's no Reid there's no
reconstructing that relationship he's
put himself by violating his contract
let's say with the transcendent and also
with society and also with his own
spirit he's put himself outside the
possibility of redemption and that's why
he says the punishment is greater than I
could bear there's no hope left right so
he's in hell for all intents and
purposes behold thou hast driven me out
this day from the face of the earth and
from thy face shall I be hid and I shall
be a fugitive and a vagabond in the
earth and it shall come to pass that
everyone who finds me will will kill me
and God says therefore whoever slayeth
Cain vengeance shall be taken on him
Sevenfold and the Lord set a mark onto
Cain lest any finding him should kill
him now that's interesting you think why
in the world would God protect Cain well
the next part of the story actually
tells you that you have a family I have
a family
your brother kills my son so what
you I come and I kill your father and
your cousin and then you think well I
killed your father and your cousin I'm
going to come back and I'm going to kill
four of your people and then I come back
and say yeah no problem it's sixteen to
you this time and then you come back and
you say sixteen a let's try for
thirty-two and so this is what happens
this is actually why justice systems are
set up by the way you go there's a bunch
of reasons justice systems are set up
and one is to punish the guilty that's
one the other is to have the guilty
repent that's two to maintain social
order
that's three here's another one that no
one ever thinks about back thirty years
ago the governor of Massachusetts whose
name I forget was running for president
and while he was governor of
Massachusetts he had released a number
of prisoners one of whom his name was I
think Willie
maybe Hortense doesn't really matter and
when Willie was released on this program
he went out and raped someone and
perhaps killed them I can't remember but
it doesn't matter that the rape is good
enough and the governor was asked during
a debate what he would do if a relief
prisoner had raped his daughter or his
wife and he gave a very weak answer what
was his name he did a very weak answer
of something about you know letting the
law take its due course and that's the
wrong answer right the right answer is I
would be compelled with every fiber of
my being to hunt that person down and to
tear them into bits but I won't do it
now what so what's the purpose of the
justice system it's to alleviate you
from the responsibility of revenge
that's what it's for
because otherwise what happens you kill
one I kill two you kill four I kill
eight you kill sixteen and soon
everyone's at war and so God protects
Cain to stop that from happening to stop
the feud from emerging because those
things can go forever and then from
transforming the entire society into a
state of war and so what's also so I'll
tell you the rest of the story and Cain
went out from the presence of the Lord
and
well in the Land of Nod on the East of
Eden and Cain knew his wife and she
conceived and bare Enoch etc so now you
have a genealogy right so Cain starts to
have a family you have a genealogy and
so a number of people are named in the
lineage and so and it tells you what
this is sort of an attempt to describe
how things came about so this is like
the naming of the heroes of old and so
you have Enoch who builds the city you
have jebel who is the father of those
who dwell in tents and of those who have
cattle you have Jubal who is the father
of musicians and Zillah
who bore tubal Cain now tubal Cain is a
very interesting person
by tradition tubal Cain is the first
artificer of weapons of war so Cain's
descendent after multiple generations is
the person who produces weapons of war
alright and so so there's another bit of
the story within which that needs to be
placed in context and Lamech who's one
of the grandchildren of Cain says unto
his wife that wives Adah and Zillah hear
my voice ye wives of Lamech hearken unto
my speech for I have slain a man to my
wounding and a young man to my hurt okay
so what he's saying is he he's been
involved in a murder
if can be a vote Avenged Sevenfold truly
Lamech seventy and Sevenfold and so
there's the implication there that the
tit for tat process has begun Cain kills
Abel Abel Cain's children kill seven
Cain's grandchildren kill seventy fold
and then tubal Cain pops up on the
horizon and he's the person who makes
artifices of war and so the story in its
fragmentary manner ties the individual
psychopathology that's resentful and
revenge seeking to the proclivity for
broad scale warfare and this really hit
me because I was interested particularly
in what was happening in the Nazi camps
with the guards
because the guards were gratuitously
cruel and I was very curious about that
and so here's an interesting story this
was in a book called ordinary Germans
Hitler's willing executioner's and it
was a book that was written about 30
years ago that challenged the idea that
the Nazi phenomena was top-down order
following which I don't believe by the
way I think that's a very weak weak
hypothesis fascistic societies are
fascistic at every single level of
organization spiritually within the
family within the local community it's
like a holograph it's the same
absolutely everywhere it's not top-down
I mean there are leaders who get
produced and maybe they catalyze it but
to blame it on the leaders is to forget
about the process by which the leaders
come to be so no you don't get a past
that way so here's one of the things
that happened as the Nazis started to
lose the war so here's what you should
have done if you were a Nazi and you
wanted to win the war you should have
enslaved the Jews and the gypsies and
had them work right you have the head
should have had them work for the
benefit of the victory and then if you
wanted to liquidate them afterwards
that's the logical thing to do if you
want to win and we assume that Hitler
wanted to win but that's not a very
intelligent assumption why would you
assume that he wasn't exactly a good guy
so why should we assume that he was
aiming at the good that he was promoting
even in his own terms right
the glorious everlasting fourth Third
Reich right let a rule for a thousand
years and be a bastion of civilization
in music because that's the sort of
thing he purported to be interested in
well so what do you do with the Jews and
the gypsies well round them up fine it
slave them fine you don't kill them you
certainly don't devote a substantial
proportion of your war resources while
you're losing to accelerate the rate at
which the extermination is taking place
because that's a bit counterproductive
unless what you're aiming at is the
maximum possible mayhem in the shortest
period of time well so what happened as
the Germans started to lose the war did
Hitler lose faith in his own ability no
he believed that the Germans had
betrayed him with weakness and so he was
perfectly willing to accelerate the rate
at which Germany was losing the war and
so when
Hitler and his minions have the choice
here's the choice you can suspend your
unnecessary demolition of people win the
damn war and then pick it up afterwards
or while you're losing you can just
accelerate the mayhem even though it's
counterproductive it's like what they
pick well they pick to accelerate demand
and so to me there's an old
psychoanalytic idea I think this was
derived by you you can't figure out what
someone is doing or why look at the
outcome and infer the motivation if it
produces mayhem perhaps it was aiming at
mayhem now you know you have to use that
dictum carefully if someone's irritating
you you know maybe it's because you're
irritable that you should sort yourself
out but maybe it's because they're
actually aiming at irritating you and
that's the actual motivation so perhaps
not but it's another tool in your
analytical armament so and so you see
well this is the thing about warfare
that's so interesting about about
because you can you can attribute it to
territoriality you can attribute it to a
war for resources that's what the I
would say wretchedly simple-minded
economists presume people fight over
scarce resources it's like hey we're a
little bit more sophisticated than that
and first of all what resources are you
talking about the bloody idiot had
nothing they live perfectly well what
did they have snow and seal blubber
you know people can live and
unbelievably deprived conditions and so
the idea that there are natural
resources that we fight over because
there's a shortage of them is a pretty
oversimplified view of human beings it's
like well why do people fight well maybe
they fight sometimes for good reasons
but very very frequently they fight for
bad reasons and those bad reasons are
our personal as well as socio-cultural
and economic you know if you are a Nazi
prison guard for example whatever
pathologies you were carrying around in
your destructive little soul whatever
element of Kane was deeply embedded in
you had the opportunity to be manifest
fully at every moment of your waking
existence right you have these people
who are completely beholden to you with
no rights whatsoever to
you could do whatever your evil little
heart determined think well maybe that
was a motivation for putting them there
to begin with and all the cover story
about well we're trying to build the
Third Reich and we're trying to
stabilize the state and we're trying to
do all these good things maybe that's
just a cover story for the real
motivation which is nothing but but what
the construction of death camps that
killed 6 million people how about that
and the obliteration of 120 million
people on the planet and the end oh and
the and the leaving of European runes
maybe that was the motivation or are we
going to attribute to Hitler the highest
possible motives say no it's an
archetypal manifestation of Cain now
he's going to put up a front it says I'm
your savior it's like well destructive
people think that Cain is their Savior
let's take a break for 15 minutes so ok
so
the next thing that happens these
stories were sewed together right to
make something that resembles a coherent
text and there's this literary athletic
no there's a literary technique known as
metonymy and metonymy is the
juxtaposition of two things beside one
another with the implication that
because they're juxtaposed they are
causally they're related in some
important matter to one another and so
the stories are sequenced and the
there's an implicit the stories are
sequenced in a particular manner and you
might operate under the assumption that
that sequencing occurred because the
sequencer who was an editor or a group
of editors they called that person to
read actor but they have no idea if it
was one person or many people who
organized these texts into something
resembling a coherent story so imagine
the stories evolved somewhat
independently and then they were
organized so that they produced what
approximated the coherent narrative it's
not entirely coherent because there are
paradoxical claims say at the level of
the sentence so for example the creation
order in the first story in Genesis
isn't exactly the same as the creation
order in the second story and you know
people who insist upon the literal truth
of the Bible whatever that means
is are bothered by those contradictions
and turn themselves into knots trying to
iron them out and fair enough right
because you want the story to be
coherent but you know that's sort of
it's important but it's also beside the
point
you don't want to focus on one level of
analysis at the exclusion of all the
other levels of analysis that's probably
the right way to think about it now the
fact that these stories are sequence in
a particular manner and that that kind
of makes sense implies that there's some
sort of narrative coherence underneath
driving forward otherwise they would be
nothing but a random assemblage of
stories and they're by no means random
that's for sure they're selected and
edited and put together in a particular
manner by and then stored that way and
dealt with in a particular manner by
thousands of people over many many years
what happens after Cain and Abel is
while there's an interlude which is
this interlude and it's kind of a bridge
and and there's a lot packed into it too
although I'm not going to take it apart
very much says so this is after after
the Cain and Abel story and it came to
pass when men began to multiply on the
face of the earth and daughters were
born unto them but the sons of God saw
the daughters of men that they were fair
and then took them wives of all which
they chose and there were giants in the
earth in those days and also after that
when the sons of God came into the
daughters of men and they bare children
to them the same became mighty men which
are of old men of renown okay so I
already pointed out that if you go back
just a little bit you see that the
descendants of Cain are represented as
founders of institutions right there are
Enoch who builds the city and an adder
or jabal who is the father of those who
dwell in tents and of those who own
cattle and then there's Jubal who's the
father of all that are musicians and so
on so one of the things that you see in
in myths very frequently is that if
there's a pattern of behavior that's
characteristic of the culture that
pattern of behavior is attributed to a
hero who was in the past who was the
first person who did that and so you
might say well what does that mean well
it means in Parkton there was the first
person who did that although more likely
there was an assemblage of people who
aggregated that particular ability say
the ability to play music across a very
large amount of time but these are pre
literate people right and they're trying
to remember the past and so what happens
Mircea Eliade documented this quite well
is that that aggregation of people gets
collapsed into a single meta person and
that's the hero of old and so and I
already talked about how this works is
that you know there are admirable people
and then you can tell a story about an
admirable person and then you can
extract a story out of the set of
admirable people and you keep building
higher and higher order admirable people
until you extract out at the top what's
ultimately admirable and this is
actually an indication of that process
occurring the Giants that are
referred to in this particular phrase
are the heroes of the past who
established the traditions on which the
society exists and so that's all
compacted into this little paragraph so
this little paragraph here there were
giants in the earth in those days and
after that when the sons of God came
into the daughters of men and they bare
children to them the same became mighty
men which were of old men of renown well
you could hardly say I think there's
very little difference between what I
just told you and what this story says I
mean it says it as if it was something
that literally occurred but in some
sense it doesn't exactly say that it
says well the ancient landscape was a
landscape of heroic adventurers it's
like well we do that to our own history
right I mean even when we consider it
literal history we don't pick people at
random to historic I sweep ick people
who had some substantive impact and tell
stories about them and and they're
emblematic in some sense of the spirit
of striving that characterizes humanity
and and so you can't have history
without some mythologies ation because
the mythologies ation occurs at the
level of the selection of the entities
about which you're going to weave the
historical tale so okay so anyway so
there's little there's a little
interlude there that it talks about the
appearance of heroes in the past but
then it's just that's just done with
very very rapidly and then we move into
another story this is the story of Noah
so the way it looks to me is that the
the part of Genesis that I'm going to
talk to you about ends with the flood
myth and also with the Tower of Babel
and so the flood myth is the demolition
of everything that came before and the
Tower of Babel in some sense is exactly
the same thing so there's two chaotic I
mean it's like the fall occurs in stages
there's paradise and then Adam and Eve
fall into culture and then Cain and Abel
Cain falls into chaos and then the
entire society falls into chaos and the
flood comes and the Tower of Babel is
produced
and then that's the end of the truly
archaic parts of the Bible and so what
that seems to me what's happening it's
very sophisticated is that there's a
implicit causal narrative being warrant
woven about the manner in which Cain
responds and the probability that human
beings are going to deteriorate and the
flood is going to come so and God saw
that the wickedness of man was great in
the earth and that every imagination of
the thoughts of his heart was only evil
continually and it repented the Lord
that he had made man on earth and it
grieved him at his heart
well we already encountered a story like
that once already right that happened in
the martyr story where time out and
absolute give rise to the elder gods and
they kill absolute which was not very
smart idea right they demolish the sub
structure of their stable society and of
course chaos comes flooding back well
what does it mean to say that human
beings let's see to say that the
wickedness of man was great in the earth
and that every imagination of the hearts
of his own thoughts of his heart was
only evil continually is not much
different than to say that people are
acting in a manner that demolishes the
cultural structure now we've already
even pointed out that the cultural
structure that happens in this story was
produced by the heroic Giants of the
past right and we've also noted that
what Kane is objecting to in his Kane
like manner is the social structure
which isn't rewarding properly and the
transcendence that's above that and the
spirit of logos itself he's rejecting
all that okay so the issue here is that
when that sort of evil is produced
exactly as when AB sue is Slade Slade I
guess that's right by the by the Elder
Gods then all hell breaks loose all
chaos comes back now time at if you
remember correctly is the god of the
salt water goddess of the salt water and
so the return of time at and the flood
are mythologically similar ideas now
Elia has taken apart flood myths from
all over the world and he made two
brilliant comments about them and there
are also akin to some degree to what you
can see
the Egyptian story about Seth and the
corruption of the state so because the
Egyptians figured out that there's
always a power working within the state
let's say that corrupted it now that was
set and that was always working for its
overthrow it's an idea like Satan and I
said that the the word Seth becomes the
word Satan through Coptic Christianity
so so the le adds I deal with this that
things fall apart of their own accord
merely because they aged that that's the
first motif in the flood story and
that's only to say that if you build
something it decays if you build
something and you just leave it the hell
alone
it will soon not work right and that's
entropy so one of the reasons that the
flood always threatens is merely because
of entropy and you see that reflected in
the Egyptian story because one of the
reasons that Osiris falls prey to Seth
is because he's old you know he was a
great hero when he was young and created
the Egyptian state like the men of
renown but now he's old and it's worse
he's be willfully blind but that's the
next thing but the fact that he's all is
just to start things fall apart of their
own accord
so once something is given to you you
have to maintain it just to ensure its
continued existence and so you actually
you actually have a contract with most
of the things that you own it's it's
like a it's like a moral contract let's
say you have a car well you've decided
that you're going to sacrifice to have
the car and so you you performed an
ethical calculation but the car was only
worth the sacrifice as long as it
functions as a car and so what that
means is that to justify the sacrifice
you've made to have the car you have to
maintain the car because otherwise
you're acting out the proposition that
the thing you sacrificed for actually
didn't have any value and so you're
obliterating that as a useful contract
and you run into the situation where the
car will just deteriorate of its own
accord and then you won't have a car at
all well so let's say how do you speed
the process by which your car
deteriorates well that's easy you're
driving it along the road and it starts
to make a ticking noise tick tick tick
tick and you think I should go have that
ticking noise checked because you've
heard it and then you think nah it won't
matter it's like yeah
probably it'll matter and what does
matter mean well matter is mother that's
chaos to you no matter but what it means
is that that little ticking noise is the
birthplace of time at in your car that's
a good way of thinking about it is that
it's your first indication that the
dragon of chaos is going to manifest
itself in your car that happens when you
I've got a funny story about that so I
had a friend in in in graduate school
someone I really liked but I wouldn't
call her mikela mechanically inclined
let's put it that way and she had an old
Honda and those things were notorious
for rusting out this is thirty years ago
when they were first produced they
weren't adapted well to Canadian winters
and we used to go in her car in her
Honda and it got a little on the scary
side because it was so rusty underneath
that you can actually see through the
floorboards and that actually made me
nervous because if you can see through
the floorboards that means that they're
not really floorboards what they are is
like rust and so I mentioned the fact
that that might be a problem to her a
couple of times but she was sort of
blithe about it and one day she was
driving down st. Lawrence Street in
Montreal which is the main street
running roughly north and south and her
hood popped up it bent and popped up
spontaneously and so she was pretty
curious about that and so she was with
this friend of hers who was just as
clueless mechanically as she was which
is really quite remarkably clueless and
so they pulled off into a service
station and had the guy come out look at
it and well he he opened the hood
obviously and what had happened was the
body had fallen off the frame so and
what had happened was the shock which is
like supposed to be attached to the car
had pushed up through the through the
hood so literally that car body had like
fallen onto the ground and but she was
she managed to drive the car okay so
look that's I wouldn't exactly call that
willful blindness because perhaps there
was an element of willful blindness she
didn't know anything about mechanics but
you get the point right it's like let's
say she would have been in a fatal
accident you might say well you can
shake your fist at God for producing the
circumstances but you know the fact that
you could see through the floorboards
that's probably something that you might
have paid attention to and so
always the question is if things fall
apart around you to what degree is it
the mere tendency of things to
degenerate entropically because they do
that of their own accord or have you
sped the probability of decay by failing
to pay attention when with our little
snake manifests itself inside your
paradise and it's always it's always a
question
so when here's a here's an example an
interesting example I think so
I've thought about the actual floods
like the New Orleans flood
okay so New Orleans is built where there
are floods everyone knows that and it's
a major port in the United States a huge
part of American trade goes down the
rivers to New Orleans
so there was a reason it was built where
it was even though it was a dangerous
place to build it and in order to
maintain New Orleans they had to build
these levees that kept the water back
now the American what is it American
Army Corps of Engineers if I remember
correctly was responsible for building
and maintaining the levees and the dikes
okay Holland is also built underwater as
you may or may not know and they build
huge dikes to keep the ocean back so
they could reclaim the land and that's
basically Holland Holland is an
unbelievably organized society and part
of the reason is is it isn't land it's
underwater and so if you're not bloody
well awake in Holland then the ocean
comes in and you all drown and so the
Dutch are very very careful about such
things and they build their dikes so
that they calculate storm intensity and
then they calculate the intensity of the
worst storm in 10,000 years and then
they build the dikes to withstand that
storm the Army Corps of Engineers built
the dikes in New Orleans to withstand
the worst storm in a hundred years and
they knew that was insufficient and New
Orleans Louisiana is an unbelievably
corrupt state and you can't dump money
in there to fix things because people
just steal all the money so and then
nothing gets fixed and so then what
happens there's a hurricane and then
what happens there's a flood and
everybody says why would God send the
flood and answer that is well was there
a flood or where the dikes not high
enough and that's what's so interesting
is that it's always this is a great
father versus great mother
conundrum if a system failed is it
because of the surround overwhelming the
system
or is it because the system was
insufficiently awake and doomed itself
okay so Eliot its take on the flood myth
is this God comes along and floods the
world periodically why and that that's
the catastrophic influx of chaos right
so chaos will wipe you out from time to
time why
well entropy does in your conceptual
schemes and your willful blindness
speeds the process and remember that's
what the Egyptians said about Osiris
right they said he was old he was a
great king a man of renown but he was
old but he was also willfully blind and
it was the combination of his age and
his willful blindness that allowed Seth
to chop them up into pieces and and
depose them and so that would that
ferret out it's brilliant right it's
like why the states fall apart because
the structures get old and no one's
taking care of them and people have
their eyes closed and so it's the same
situation it's the same situation in the
flood myths it's like well yeah things
fall apart they're going to flood but if
you were awake enough and you were on
top of it then you could continually
stave that off and actually partly what
you're doing because you're alive is
staving off entropy like you're an anti
em tropic process it's a really good
definition of life there's a great
physicist named Erland Schrodinger who
wrote a book called what is life and
that's the fundamental thesis of the
book you're always trying to stave off
entropy what's the best way to stave off
entropy decay chaos
keep your eyes open that's the rule shut
your eyes especially two things you know
you should see the flood comes and
that's the evil of man that's laid out
in this story because that's the worst
sort of perhaps it's not the worst it's
one of the primary sins so to speak that
will bring about the flood we already
talked about the other things that
characterized Cain's attitude so
here we go so gods upset because he made
man on earth and it grieved him at his
heart and God says I will destroy man
whom I have created from the face of the
earth both man and beast and the
creeping thing and the fowls of the air
for I repent that I've made them but
Noah found grace in the eyes of the Lord
okay so that's an interesting thing so
here what we have is the question is the
whole worlds in chaos at this point
right in this point the story and the
chaos is of multiple sorts it arose from
the fall it rose from the emergence of
self-consciousness it emerged safe arose
from the sins of Cain like things are
not going well it's multiple levels of
collapse and it's got to the point where
God saying this is a mess like it's such
a mess that the whole thing has to be
washed away the first fall wasn't enough
even Cain's collapse wasn't enough we're
going to just scrub the whole bloody
thing clean so it's it's the ultimate in
traumatic collapses the question is well
what do you do in the face of the
ultimate in traumatic collapses and the
answers in the story so know as someone
who finds fate who finds favor in the
eyes of God so he's like Abel there's
something that Noah's doing right it's
going to enable him to ride out the
storm and so the question hits the same
question do you want to have a life
where there's no storms or do you want
to have a life where you can ride out
the storms that's the issue right are
you behind the dikes or do you build a
boat do you tap them the boat that's the
same idea and so the idea here is that
the thing that rides out the chaos is
the thing that builds and captain's the
boat it's another dominance hierarchy
idea what should be at the top well it's
the top of something that doesn't get
flooded out as well what should be at
the top well it's to be the boat builder
and to be the captain of the boat it's
not to be hidden from the flood
precisely and so I mean here's a here's
here's something to think about identity
identity politics because that's what
we're up to our neck it okay are you who
you are can I box you in will you accept
that as an identity so I could do that
lots of ways you're male you're Asia
you're you
right there's things about you that I
can derive because of your putative
membership in a set of different groups
the problem with doing that is that the
number of groups that I can assign you
to is without end so I have to pick
arbitrary groups to assign you to and
you can accept that if you want but
there's no evidence that those are the
proper canonical groups but maybe you're
happy about that because now you've been
assigned membership in a group and
that's your identity okay so the
question is well fine what happens when
that identity is flown into pieces then
what well here's here's the answer to
some degree and this is the answer
that's embedded in the story of Noah
if you want to withstand chaos do you
want to be who you are or do you want to
be the thing that changes who you are
constantly that's the question and
that's the difference that's the
difference there's a categorical
difference in identity are you who you
are or are you the thing that could
continually be more than you are and
that's the thing that isn't the stable
identity it's not the initial state it's
also not the state of being in chaos
that nihilistic state let's say and it's
not even the state of reformulations
that occurs after you've gone through
the process it's the state of
continually going through the process so
you can identify with the thing that
trends you can identify identify with
the thing that you are or you can
identify with the thing that transforms
who you are right and that's the same as
the state subjugating itself to the
individual because the individual is the
thing that transforms the state and what
the state should do the states necessary
because obviously it organizes all of us
into peaceful cooperation and
competition the states necessary then
the question is is the state the highest
good an answer that is well it can't be
because it's old and dead and blind and
so if the state becomes the highest good
then you're occupied by the spirit of
something that's old and dead and blind
well that's not only not good for you
because then you're old and dead and
blind but it's also bad for the state
because as soon as the state gets old in
dead and blind God gets unhappy with it
and the chaos comes in and washes it
away so it seems like a bad solution so
what's the proper solution you
subordinate your group identity to the
identity that transforms your identity
right and the state subordinates its
power to the vision and articulation of
the individual because that's what
revives the state and so that's what
these stories are trying to stumble
towards roughly speaking so Noah found
grace in the eyes of the Lord why well
Noah was a just man and perfect in his
generations and Noah walked with God now
remember in the Adam and Eve story Adam
was walking with God to begin with but
then he got all self-conscious and hid
behind a bush and when God came to walk
with him he blamed his wife for his
insufficiencies which I still think
that's such an unbelievably comic story
I just can't believe it it's so
absolutely ridiculous but that's exactly
what happened while you have Noah here
and Noah Noah's like a counter another
counterpart to some degree to Cain no as
a just man and he walks with God and so
he's oriented properly and because he's
oriented properly when the flood comes
not only does he manage to get through
it as an individual he manages to get
through it with his family and he saves
and while he saves he roughly saves the
world that's how the story puts it
forward I mean it's an ark and it's full
of animals you know it's it's got a
child story element to it fact I suspect
it probably was a story that was
primarily told to children you know it's
like a fable but it's a fable with Punch
like the Pinocchio story is a fable with
Punch it's like well yeah there's going
to be a flood there's always a flood
there's always a flood so who are you if
you want to get through the flood well
then you're Noah you're the thing that
builds the boat you're the thing that
acts justly you're the thing that walks
with God we already know what that means
you identify with the transcendent
that's like Geppetto pointing to the
star before the transformation process
that occurs with Pinocchio it's you're
identifying with the benevolent spirit
of the state so you have a relationship
with the transcendent and the benevolent
spirit of the state and you're also
identified with the capacity to generate
chaos
of order and the reverse that's what it
means to walk with God roughly speaking
it's across all of those dimensions so
what does that do it gives you the power
to withstand the flood and to bring
people and and and being itself and
civilization along with you and that's
the story of Noah so it's a precursor
it's another Abel as a precursor to the
idea of the redeeming Messiah right Noah
is a precursor to the idea of the
redeeming Messiah you could think about
the mask proto messiahs or proto meta
Heroes something like that and they
manifest themselves they're part of the
Giants that walked in the past and
they're embodied their attempts embodied
in story to elucidate the the triangle
that's at the top of the pyramid right
the eye that's at the top of the pyramid
so so I won't tell you the rest of the
Noah story because I don't think it's
necessary for us to to - to delve into
the - the more narrative details but I
do want - so it's a pretty rough I can
point out it's a pretty rough story
every living substance was destroyed
which was upon the face of the ground
both Man and cattle and creeping things
in the fall of the heaven and they were
destroyed from the earth and Noah only
remained alive and they that were with
him in the Ark it's a very terrifying
story you know and and it's worth
attending to because we are currently in
a period of extreme chaos so okay so
anyway this works out God's had enough
he's killed is enough he's killed enough
of everything it's a it's a traumatic
occurrence we can put it that way the
waters recede and God God is done for
the time being and so then this is what
happens at the end so the ark settle
down there unloading it and creation is
reborn and so then you think well what
sets things right again between man and
God and the story says that Noah built
in our altar unto the Lord and took of
every clean beast and of every clean
fowl and offered burnt offerings on the
altar so it's the same idea here it's
that the same idea that you started to
see emerging in the Cain
Abell story what is it that sets things
right between man and God
sacrifice so the flood comes then Noah
makes the proper sacrifices right it's
part of reestablishing the proper order
he makes the proper sacrifices and so
God is happy with the sacrifices which
is a good thing given that he's pretty
ordinary and-and-and the Lord smelled a
sweet savour so remember I told you
before that the reason people thought
that this would work was because the
smoke would rise up and God would be
able to detect whether or not the the
sacrifice was of high quality well you
have it written right there you know
it's very concrete eyes dim egde of the
archetypal spirit right the Lord smelled
a sweet savour and said in his heart I
will not curse the ground any more for
man's sake for the imagination of man's
heart is evil from this youth neither
will i again smite any more every living
thing as I have done that's pretty nice
as Noah's sacrifice actually calms down
God down to the point where he says well
I'm not going to wipe everything out
again it's like well fair enough you
know but it I would consider it somewhat
of a tenuous contract because we've seen
more than one example in the recent
century where we came bloody close to
wiping everything out again while the
earth remains seedtime and harvest and
cold in heat in summer and winter and
day and night shall not cease
neither again will i smite any more
every living thing as I have done so all
right so that's that he basically tells
Noah the same thing again that he told
Adam at the beginning of the Genesis
story so fine and then he tells them a
bunch of rules which I could go into but
at the moment I won't but I want to show
you that
basically what God I guess I should do
this to some degree God lays out a bunch
of rules so you could think about it as
a precursor to what happens in the story
of Exodus where the Ten Commandments are
revealed so this is like a foreshadowing
of that story no one makes the proper
sacrifices and God says okay fine here's
the rules follow these rules and then
they're laid out and things will go okay
with you that's the covenant that's the
agreement between the end you could say
that's the agreement between the
individual and the spirit of the state
that's one way of looking at but it's
not enough because it isn't merely the
spirit of the state that's being
negotiated with it's the spirit of the
state it's the spirit of that which
transcends the state and it's the spirit
of the moral order that's within the
individual all three of those things are
being negotiated simultaneously the
proper sacrifices are made the proper
rules are laid out and the idea is that
there'll be a good balance between order
and chaos as a consequence as long as
people continue to play by the rules so
that's the offerin fundamentally so part
that seems to work out and then this one
I think is extremely interesting it's
also very short it took me a very very
long time to to understand this
all right so this is after the story of
Noah so what happens is you get this
situation where things descend into
chaos and there's a great flood so
that's sort of like the ultimate chaos
story and I think of it as it there so
you imagine when things fall apart one
possibility is that they fall into chaos
the other possibility is something like
they become hyper conceptualized in
hyper orderly and so then the state
itself which would be the antidote to
chaos actually becomes a source of
pathology and I think that that's what's
being hinted at in the story of the
Tower of Babel so here's what happens is
that human beings I'll read it to you
this is this has to do with Noah's
descendants it's a flip into another
story and it came to pass as they
journeyed from the east oh yes
and all the days of Noah were 950 years
and he died news story and the whole
earth was of one language and one speech
everybody's getting along fine in their
tribal organization let's say it's
homogenous they can all speak to one
another and they all speak the same
language and it came to pass as they
journeyed from the east that they found
a plain in the land of Shinar and they
dwelt there and they said to one another
go to let us make brick and burn them
thoroughly and they had brick for stone
and slime had they for mortar and they
said go to go to let us build a city and
a tower whose top may reach unto heaven
and let us make a name lest we be
scattered abroad upon the face of the
whole earth
okay so what's happening here only the
bear this is this what this story means
is very deeply implicit in the story
it's hinting at it and I think it's
because it was really beyond the power
of the conceptualization of the people
who generated this story to elaborate it
to any great detail but I think what it
means is this is that there's a guy
named Robin I think it's Robin Dunbar
and one of the things that Dunbar has
done is do a very in detail correlation
analysis of cortical expansion and group
size and what he showed is
that if you if you plot primates by
cortical size let's say you corrected
for body size you plot primates by
cortical size and then you plot the size
of their social groups you see a very
tight relationship between the size of
the social group and the size of the
cortex the optimal human social group is
like two hundred individuals is
something like that which is maybe
roughly the number of people that you
can reasonably track on Facebook after
that it's like well there's names but
you don't know those people
you're not capable of tracking social
dynamics there any more complex than
that particles you have other problems
to solve and so one of the things that
has been observed is that human groups
tend to fractionate if they start to
exceed 200 and maybe that's partly
because you can't keep track of the
complexity but there's another
constraint which is you want your group
to be big enough so that it protects you
but you want it to be small enough so
that you can climb to the top because so
when the group gets really really really
really big well maybe it can protect you
although it also doesn't give a damn
about you like once you're 160
thousandth of the group like you are at
the University of Toronto we're 130
millionth of the country or maybe 1 300
millionth of Europe which is partly why
Europe is going to fragment because
that's just not enough right you're just
not enough there that this the group is
too big what happens
you keep aggregating the group it gets
more and more powerful and you can think
of that as something that has the
capacity to replace the transcendent
right will make a society that's perfect
it's like a utopian vision that's what I
see happening in this story it's like
we'll make something so great on the
part of human beings that it will reach
up to heaven itself which means it will
take the place of God that's what it
means that's exactly what the Communists
did in Soviet Russia that's what they
tried to do in China too and so that's
why you ended up with people like Stalin
as the God so you talk about getting
what you deserve so anyways so you build
these monolithic enterprises that will
let's call them state enterprises and
the idea there is that the state the
hyper organized and all-inclusive state
can bring about Utopia that's what it
means to reach to heaven so what happens
so god gets wind of that
and he says blood says the Lord came
down see the city in the tower which the
children of men built and the Lord said
Behold the people is one and now they
all have one language and this they
begin to do and now nothing will be
restrained from them which they have
imagined to do go to let us go down and
therefore confound their language that
they may not understand one another's
speech
what's interesting because it's sort of
the story kind of portrays it as
jealousy on God's part right it's like
oh these these human beings they're
they're building so magnificently that
they're starting to challenge my
Dominion well I'm going to go down there
and play a trick or two law on them and
that'll that'll take care of that so
what happens the people within the so
the group gets bigger and bigger and
bigger and bigger and bigger and what
happens it starts to fragment that is
what happens that's exactly what happens
that's part of the reason why the
totalitarian state enterprise to replace
the transcendent with structure that's
one of the reasons it's doomed as you
pull more and more people in what
happens is you start to pull in chaos
itself and that starts to fragment the
order here is an interesting thing I
think that's happening with the soul the
LGBT power groups are exclusion excluded
groups right and so it started out with
gay rights and then one of the things
that's happened it's so interesting so
you could think of there was a normative
group and there was excluded people okay
and so one section of the excluded
people stood up and said hey you know
enough of this explosion so we're going
to categorize ourselves and we're going
to fight for recognition as the excluded
we're going to fight to be included but
what happens is well it's L and then
it's lb and then it's lb G and then it's
LGBT and the last thing I saw which was
actually handed to the medical students
in at the University of Toronto there's
20 letters why well because you can't
this is tangentially related to this
story only you can't come up with a
category of the things that don't fit
inside categories because there's an
infinite number of things that don't fit
inside categories and so when you try to
build a category out of all uncatted
oracle entities all that happens is
defragment because there's actually no
unity there and one of the things you
are starting to see is that there's
power battles emerging on the part of
the excluded on the left and it's
inevitable because and I think that's
what this story is trying to represent
is that you can't build the state up
beyond a certain size if you Delia will
fragment and fall apart the people
within it will no longer speak the same
language and they'll they'll they'll
disperse themselves to different corners
of the earth and so I think we're
actually in real danger of forgetting
this and one of the things that I saw
read a couple of ominous things so if
you plot the size of economic
catastrophes over the last thirty years
they're getting bigger each time so
that's scary now part of that is because
the world economy is getting bigger and
so maybe you have to control for that
but the magnitude of the chaos has been
increasing with each collapse okay one
of the things that came out of the last
collapse 2008 was the government
rescuing collapsed companies like AIG
and the Royal Bank of Scotland which by
the way was the biggest company in the
world no one knows that but Royal Bank
of Scotland collapsed it was the biggest
company in the world and AIG was the
insurer
of insurers and so it collapsed too they
were rescued by the government and maybe
fair enough
but one of the motifs that came out of
that was the idea of too big to fail
well this story says wait a second it
says too big means definite failure it
means inevitable failure and that
strikes me as highly probable is that
there's a warning in this story although
it's it's just it's a bear story right
it's only four or five lines it's just
the outlines but it's placed in a very
particular place it's placed right after
the flood right it's like well there's
the nihilistic chaos of the flood and
then there's the temp totalitarian
temptation to build hyper structures
that can theoretically replace the
transcendent well what happens you build
a hyper structure net fragments from
within and then people don't speak the
same language and they and they you know
distribute themselves sort of
chaotically on the surface of the earth
so
therefore is the name of it called Babel
because the Lord did there confound the
language of all the earth and from
thence did the Lord scattered them
abroad upon the face of all the earth I
think the other issue too is is that
what's the problem with the homogenize a
ssin of a group it's like you bring
everyone into the group and then they're
all the same uniformity well the
advantages you can understand everyone
the disadvantages there's no variability
left right there's no variability
everyone is a clone of everyone else and
that's great if you know where you're
going and you know how to get there but
it's really really bad if the underlying
structure shifts on you because the fact
that you're adapted to one situation
hyper adapted to one situation might
mean that you're content completely not
adapted to the next situation you build
groups that are too big and too
homogenous they're effective but only
within the limited range of their map
and it's the map no longer functions
then the whole thing sinks and that's I
think what happens in this particular
story and then okay at the end of that
then what happens is that soon
afterwards and I think perhaps
immediately afterwards the story of
Abraham emerges and that's really I
would say that's when the the prime
myths the primal myths take on a more
historical element and history you know
roughly speaking history as we know it
begins something like 6,000 years ago so
and then then you know the rest of the
biblical stories proceed apace from
there what basically happens is that
this is something that was well mapped
out by Northrop Frye and you'd think at
the University of Toronto that you all
would have been encouraged to read
Northrop Frye because he was perhaps the
greatest literary scholar that the
University of Toronto ever produced and
what he he outlined the Old Testament
very interestingly he said that what
happens after these initial stories is
that the state arises so it's like the
Tower of Babel is continually rebuilt
over and over it's the state of Israel's
Israelis Israelite to get their act
together build a state what happens they
get corrupt the Prophet comes up and
says you better watch out because what
you're doing is not making God happy and
the prophets are very brave because they
come forward that the case are
authoritarian they could kill them at an
instant but the profits are moved by
walking with God let's say for lack of a
better argument they come to the king
and say look you're not caring for the
widows and the children right you think
that's okay because they're weak it's
not okay
you're breaking the Covenant you're
breaking the rules and the price for
that is what we're Esau the price for
that is the flood it's like get your act
together or you're going to be sorry now
sometimes the Kings to whom the prophets
speak listen but often they don't and
then the whole bloody state is
demolished and then the Israelites are
back like they're enslaved or they get
wiped out by their enemies or like it's
a complete bloody catastrophe that lasts
for centuries then they kind of struggle
back up and make another state and then
they get arrogant and then it gets
corrupt and then a prophet comes along
and says you know what happened last
time like well that was 600 years ago
right and I know everything now so I
don't have to pay any attention to you
it's they ignore it and then because and
the prophets say you are violating a
fundamental moral order you're supposed
to as king you're supposed to be subject
to something higher than yourself right
it's like the idea that the
Mesopotamians had that the emperor was
supposed to be an emissary of Marduk
that's why he was the Emperor because he
was a good Marduk he could confront
chaos and make order that was what gave
him his sovereignty or the Egyptian
pharaoh was a combination of Osiris and
Horus that's what gave him sovereignty
and so the idea was you get to be king
but you have to act out the spirit of
being King and if you don't do that then
well King or not all hell's going to
break loose for you and that's what the
prophets continued to say but the
Israelites you know they don't pay
enough attention and they continue to
get absolutely demolished and so the Old
Testament can be read at least in part
as the description of a sequence of the
rise and fall of States and their
descent into corruption and chaos and so
we'll leave it at that because I want to
tell you the next part of the story the
last part of the story roughly speaking
in our next lecture which is also the
last lecture so we've got about 12
minutes if we want it so if anybody has
any questions you can ask them or we can
and if you don't then we could call it a
day
so does any well it's a lot of
information so and it's a lot of strange
information so I'm curious you know it's
if it what do you make of it you're
talking about Europe around eternity so
why is why the group war side which is
America is related fate you think the
right and left can talk to each other
sure you think they speak the same
language right so you see of that
fragmenting occurring and they really
are not only are they speaking different
languages they're they really are
speaking different languages it's the
right way of thinking about it yes it's
very very dangerous you know I think the
u.s. worked for a long time first of all
because it didn't always have 300
million people it's a lot of people to
put under one umbrella now the utility
of the American system is that it is a
hierarchy right there's individuals
families towns States underneath a
somewhat loose federal structure and
that's sort of so it's not a it's not a
monolith where everyone has to speak
precisely the same language it's got
some flexibility built into its
structure because it's it's come it's
it's formulated into components which
have a certain amount of autonomy and so
far that's worked sufficiently well
whether it will and it will probably
continue to work I mean the Americans
are very very robust people and they've
gone through things that are analogous
to what they're going through now many
times god only knows right but but it's
very dangerous thing to presume that the
Americans are down for the count because
they have an uncanny ability to rise out
from mash is even stronger than they
were before but you can certainly see
the danger lurking in Europe that's
that's a different thing
like I think the European state is
doomed because I think it grew too fast
and it severed the connection between
like there's not the proper hierarchy of
identification so and people are saying
wait Brussels like who the hell are you
guys why are you making decisions for us
and we don't agree with your decision
and like are you sure that Greece and
Germany can be in the same place because
that's by no means self-evident right
the Germans aren't very happy about it
and the Greeks aren't very happy about
it and one of the rules for making an
organization is that it's a lot easier
to make a functional organization worse
than it is to make a dysfunctional
organization better and so you might say
well you've got Germany and France and
England well let's say Germany and
France powerhouses especially Germany
they can afford to bring Greece in well
maybe but there's no evidence that they
can afford it so I mean Greece is
unbelievably corrupt no one pays their
income tax that's a big problem right
and bringing them in to a union at a
high order has no effect whatsoever on
the micro behaviors and the thing is the
micro behaviors have to be rectified and
no one really knows how to do that how
do you stop a country where people don't
pay their taxes from how do you stop
people from not paying their taxes why
do we pay our taxes who knows we could
just all of a sudden decide not to you
know and the government wouldn't have
the resources to run around gathering
them all up for one reason or another
it's become customary for people in
functional Western democracies to pay
their taxes but why who knows it
would've been way easier for us just to
do what the Greeks did and pretend to
pay them you know so they're too big I
think and so the people on the right is
saying back to the nation like I
understand why they're doing that but
but the danger is the nation will
subordinate the individual and I do see
it as another example of safe spaces
it's just scales different so and that's
why I think that the proper antidote to
that to both the chaos on the left and
the order on the right roughly speaking
is to walk the proper line in the middle
and when we better do that because
things are not things are too chaotic at
the moment so it's not good maybe it's
really good that's possible but we're in
a state where I really believe we're in
a state where things could go any number
of ways and there's
no there's no predicting it so and I've
never felt that you know I mean I lived
in the 80s and you know political
correctness rose up in the 90s as well
and I can remember a lot of what
happened in the early 70s with the oil
crisis and all that so there were times
when things were shaky but they weren't
shaky the way they are now they're in
internal shakiness rather than something
that was a threat that would seem to be
imposed from the outside and that's
different and and it's it's it's it is
associated with with this intellectual
war that's going on with post-modernism
in the you Marxism and all of that as
well
so the ether of the program music on the
GPS will be especially ideal in rest
future and you mentioned that the
program probably exogamous or pronounced
and then it's picked lean on the Western
assessment what is asked for imagery a
goal-directed
and with special ability related and
they are so given that Madrid has made a
real little piece of doing it could this
account for the jungle
that's a lot of questions they're good
questions well I'll tell you a couple of
strange things that that things that I
don't really understand the first is
when we've done the analysis of the
effects of the future altering program
it has had a difference its differential
impact on men and it had a particularly
differential impact on what I would call
excluded men and so that would be
non-western ethnic minority men or or
what majority men who are doing very
well so for example at Mohawk College
the theater authoring program had a
particularly robust effect on Mohawk
College students who were men who
haven't done very well in high school
and who hadn't picked a major that had a
destination a career destination at its
end so you can imagine those people are
they have an ambiguous relationship with
the idea of education and they're not
oriented specifically towards a goal
they're not very motivated now why does
it have a differential effect on man
that's a good question well first of all
the women are doing better so it might
just be a matter of the fact that it
does better for people who aren't doing
as well and at the moment most of them
are men I don't believe I think that
might be part of it but I don't believe
that's all of it I think that part of
the reason that women are doing better
is because they're agreeable and so if a
system sets out a structure and says
here's a pathway to attainment the women
won't rebel against that they'll go
along with it and that's working very
well for them at the moment the men
especially the men on the disagreeable
end of the distribution and there's way
more men on the district disagreeable
end of the distribution then there are
women right that's what you get from if
you look at overlapping normal
distributions so there's the male just
female distribution for agreeableness
male distribution for agreeableness
tremendous overlap okay women are higher
all the really agreeable people are
women all the really disagreeable people
are men and maybe the real differences
occur at the extremes right so so and
it's a very interesting side effect of
overlapping distributions so they people
can be mostly the same but that can
still produce radical differences
disagreeable men won't do anything they
don't want to do
they just say up yours I'll go home and
play video games with you no I'm not
listening to your stupid classes and why
should I work for you
I'll just go have fun I'll do my own
thing I don't think they're motivated
and so then if you take the men who are
like that and you say okay what do you
want you can have what you want but you
have to figure out what it is so then
they write down what they want they
think oh hey well that might be worth
having so maybe I'll put some effort
into it that's what it looks like to me
now you know that's weak evidence and
this is a weak argument but I'm trying
to stretch out my understanding to
account for this but I'll tell you
something else that's really weird I
don't understand this either so more
than 90% of the people who watch my
videos on YouTube are men now that's
weird because not about 80% of
psychology students are women so that is
not what you would expect right you'd
expect that the majority of them would
be women and you might say well it's
because of the political stance I've
taken and I thought well that's possible
so I went and looked at the demographic
data because I have that well before I
did any of the political videos
eighty-five percent of my viewers were
men so it's actually increased a bit
it's increased by six percent and that's
not trivial but it was still
overwhelmingly men so that was
interesting I thought what the hell why
is that exactly
and then now I've been watching crowds
when I've been talking to them and the
crowds that have come to see me in
person this happened at the University
of Toronto free speech debate and I
actually noticed it and commented on it
before the debate took place because I
was talking about intrinsic differences
between men and women and I looked
around the room and I thought hmm
hey 80% of the people in this room are
men so I had all the men stat women and
women stand up and then all the men
stand up it said look like here's a
natural experiment for some reason 80%
of the people who showed up to this or
men now everybody thought I was kind of
cracked to to do that and it was a risk
you know and I but I thought no there's
something going on here and then what's
interesting now is that every public
appearance that I've made that's related
to the sort of topics that we're
discussing is overwhelmingly men it's
like it's like 85 to 90 percent and so I
thought wow that's weird like what the
hell's going on here exactly and then
the other thing I've noticed is that
I've been talking a lot to the crowds
that I've been talking to not about
rights but about responsibility right
because he can't have the bloody
converse what do you do it you can't
have the conversation about rights
without the conversation about
responsibility because your rights are
my responsibility that's what they are
technically so you just can't have only
half of that discussion and we're only
having half that discussion the question
is well what the hell are you leaving
out if you only have that half of the
discussion and the answer is while
you're leaving out responsibility and
then the question is well what are you
leaving out if you're leaving out
responsibility and the answer might be
well maybe you're leaving out the
meaning of life that's what it looks
like to me it's like here you are
suffering away what makes it worthwhile
right you know you're completely out
you're completely you have no idea what
you're you it's almost impossible to
describe how bad an idea that is
responsibility that's what gives life
meaning
it's like lift a load then you can
tolerate yourself right because look at
your useless easily hurt easily killed
why should you have any self-respect
that's the story of the fall pick
something up and carry it pick make it
heavy enough so that you can think yeah
well useless as I am at least I could
move that from there to there well
what's really cool about that is that
when I talk to these crowds about this
the man's eyes light up and that's very
like I've seen that phenomena because
I've been talking about this
mythological material for a long time
and I can see when I'm watching crowds
people you know their eyebrows lifter I
let light up because I put something
together for them that's what
mythological stories do so I'm not
taking responsibility for that that's
what the stories do so I save the story
people go click click click you know in
their eyes light up
but this responsibility thing that's a
whole new order of this is that young
men are so hungry for that it is
unbelievable and one of the things I've
been talking to some of the people
who've been running for the conservative
leadership in Canada and I've been
talking to them about well the
difficulties they have communicating
with young people because conservatives
what the hell are they going to sell to
young people right because being
conservative is something that happened
when you're older they can sell
responsibility no one's selling it and
the thing is for men there's nothing but
responsibility you know I was watching
The Simpsons the other day I watched the
first Simpsons episode and I
deconstructed it and so it's really
interesting so what happens in the first
Simpson episode is that it's Christmas
and Homer and Marge are going to buy
some Christmas presents but Homer
doesn't get his Christmas bonus and so
he's absolutely crushed by that and that
actually is a recurring theme in The
Simpsons where Homer loses his job or
something like that or can tonight make
enough money he's completely crushed
even though he's kind of useless
bumbling laughing fool of a guy you know
the thing that gives that show its soul
is that he's still oriented towards his
family that's what makes him honorable
is that foolish as he is he's decided to
adopt responsibility for his family and
to try to bear that and so he's not he's
a holy fool he's not a complete fool and
it's so interesting watching the story
because he suffers dreadfully as a
consequence of not being able to fulfill
his responsibilities well that's for men
women have their sets of
responsibilities they're not the same
right because they're complicated
because women of course have to take
primary responsibility for for having
infants at least but then also for
caring for them there they're structured
differently than men for biological
necessity even if it's not a
psychological issue and it's also partly
a psychological issue women know what
they have to do men have to figure out
what they have to do and if they have
nothing worth living for then they stay
Peter Pan and why the hell not
because the alternative to valued
responsibility is impulsive low-class
pleasure and you saw that in the
Pinocchio story right that's Pleasure
Island it's like well why lift the load
if there's nothing in it for you that's
another thing that we're doing to men
that's a very bad idea and to boys it's
like you're pathological and oppressive
it's like fine then why the hell am I
going to play that's if that's the
situation if I get no credit for bearing
responsibility it could bloody well be
sure I'm not going to barity but then
you know your life is useless and
meaningless and you have you're not
full of self-contempt and nihilism and
and that's not good
and so that's why I think that's what I
think's going on at a deeper level with
regards to men needing this direction
a man has to decide that he's going to
do something he has to decide that and
the different sort of animal things were
some more
yeah well you know importantly what
you're trying to do in the future
authoring process is say okay well
what's your highest value right it's the
star it's like okay what are you aiming
for you can decide man but you know
there's some criteria it should be good
for you it should be good for you in a
way that facilitates your moving forward
maybe it should be good for you in a way
that's also good for the family in the
community it should cover the the domain
of life I mean there's constraints on
what you should regard as a value but
you but within those constraints you
have the choice you have choice well the
thing is is that people will carry a
heavy load if they get to pick the
goddamn load so and they think well I
won't carry any load it's like okay fine
but then you're like the sled dog that
doesn't have a sled to pull you're just
gonna you're going to tear pieces out of
your own legs because you're bored you
know you need people are pack animals
they need they need to pull against
awake and and that's not true for
everyone it's not true particularly say
for low conscientious people I mean
maybe they're open and creative or
extroverted and some other things but
for the for the typical person they
they'll eat themselves they'll eat
themselves up unless they have a load
this is why there's such an opiate
epidemic among dispossessed white
middle-aged guys who are unemployed in
the u.s. it's like they lose their job
they're done right they despise
themselves they develop chronic pain
syndromes and depression and the chronic
pain is treated with opiates it's like
that's what we're doing so yeah that's
what it looks like to me is you you have
to and it's so interesting to watch the
young men when you talk to them about
responsibility there's a god damn
thrilled about it it just blows me away
it's like really that's what that's the
counterculture grow the hell up and do
something useful really I could do that
oh I'm so excited by that idea no one
ever mentioned that before
like rights rights rights rights Jesus
it's it's appalling it's a bit and I
feel that that's deeply felt by the
people who are who are coming out to to
listen to these sorts of things too
they've had enough of that so and they
better have because it's it's a
non-productive mode of being
responsibility man that's where the
meeting in life is so all right good one
more class thanks we'll see you next
week